<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short review of some reflections made by a nameless author upon Dr. Crisp's sermons, in a piece entituled Crispianism unmask'd with some remarks upon the union in the late agreement in doctrin among the dissenting ministers in London : subscribed the 16th of December, 1692, and that as referring unto the present debates ... / by Thomas Edwards, esq.</title>
            <author>Edwards, Thomas, fl. 1693-1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 205 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38139</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E236</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31409</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11963055</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11963055</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51623</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38139)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51623)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1006:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short review of some reflections made by a nameless author upon Dr. Crisp's sermons, in a piece entituled Crispianism unmask'd with some remarks upon the union in the late agreement in doctrin among the dissenting ministers in London : subscribed the 16th of December, 1692, and that as referring unto the present debates ... / by Thomas Edwards, esq.</title>
                  <author>Edwards, Thomas, fl. 1693-1699.</author>
                  <author>Crisp, Tobias, 1600-1643.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 34, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Will. Marshall ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata bound at end.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Antinomianism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51623:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51623:1"/>
            <p> A SHORT REVIEW OF SOME REFLECTIONS, Made by a Nameleſs Author, UPON Dr. Criſp's Sermons, In a piece, Entituled, <hi rend="blackletterType">Criſpianiſm Vnmask'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With ſome Remarks upon the Union in the late Agreement in Doctrin among the <hi>Diſſenting Miniſters</hi> in <hi>London;</hi> Subſcribed the <hi>16th</hi> of <hi>December,</hi> 1692. and that, as referring unto the preſent Debates.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Exek. 8. 7.</bibl> 
                  <hi>Behold a hole in the Wall,</hi> v. 11. <hi>Every Man his Cenſer,</hi> (i. e. At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement, or Inherent Righteouſneſs) <hi>in his Hand;</hi> (but not the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce of <hi>one,</hi> Rom. 5. 19.) v. 12. <hi>Son of Man, haſt thou ſeen what the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſe of</hi> Iſrael <hi>do in the dark, every Man in the Chambers of his Imagery?</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Prov. 17. 24.</bibl> 
                  <hi>Wiſdom is before him that hath underſtanding; but the Eyes of a Fool are in the end of the Earth,</hi>—as roving in his implicit Univerſals.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Matth. 13. 25.</bibl> 
                  <hi>While Men ſlept, his Enemy came, and ſowed Tares among the Wheat, and went his way,</hi> (i. e. would not be known, or openly Subſcribe to his Work.)</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Iſa. 28. 17.</bibl> 
                  <hi>Judgment alſo will I lay to the Line, and Righteouſneſs to the Plum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, and the Hail,</hi> (i. e. ſharp and impartial dealings, drawn from a deep and weighty Conſideration of the Divine Perfections) <hi>ſhall ſweep away the Refuge of Lies, and the Waters,</hi> (i. e. an over-powering and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Teſtimony unto the Truth by the Spirit) <hi>ſhall overflow the hiding-place.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>Latet anguis in herba.</q>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS EDWARDS,</hi> Esq;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Will. Marſhall,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Newgate-ſteeet:</hi> Where you may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied with Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi>'s Inquiry into the Goſpel-Truth. You may likewiſe be ſupplied with moſt of Dr. <hi>Owen</hi>'s, and Mr. <hi>Beverley</hi>'s Works, and likewiſe thoſe other lately Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in Vindication of Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi>'s Works. 1693.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51623:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:51623:2"/>
            <head>THE Introduction.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THere appeared lately, and that openly upon the Stage (in a Religious Senſe, or rather pretence) an <hi>Italian Quack-Salver;</hi> who fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to paſs off his Drugs with that Expedition and Succeſs, that his high Conceptions of them might poſſibly ſuggeſt him with, is withdrawn behind the Curtain, and yet we may juſtly ſuſpect his return upon us in this his <hi>Anonymous Proxy,</hi> from the Matter and Proceſs of this his Treatiſe; as <hi>Mountebanks,</hi> in their unſucceſsful Attempts, leave the Remainders of their dying, and yet reſtorative Hopes, on the Cryptical Efforts, and renewed En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of their Jeſters, or Jack-Puddings, in their managing, even the ſame Deſign, though but in Diſguiſe, as they themſelves had done before. Therefore thou wilt find that all that <hi>this our Author</hi> produces againſt Dr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> is no more as to the Matter and Manner, Ends or Deſign thereof, than what thou haſt formerly ſeen fully opened, and undeniably invalidated by others, eſpecially in a Treatiſe, called, <hi>NEONOMIANISM UNMASK'D,</hi> and <hi>A REJOYN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER</hi> by its Author, in Defence of the ſame; unto which I expect not any ſober, or tolerable <hi>Reply.</hi> The which, <hi>our preſent Latent Author,</hi> (though I am apt to think conſcious of his fault by his flattering <hi>Preamble</hi> to his bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and falſe Charge againſt the <hi>Doctor</hi>) takes no more notice of, than the Journeyman-Taylor did of his Maſter's Reproof for ſewing awry or amiſs, but deſired he might ſtitch out altogether. This <hi>our Author,</hi> as we ſhall find, doth in the Cloſe of his Treatiſe. Vain Glory, Itching Fancies, Carnal Appearances, and Prevaricatory Practiſes, are the infallible Sprouts of a ſelf-Juſticiary. Therefore, conſidering how fully the Truth, and that under a Fundamental Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration thereof, hath been from Dr. <hi>Criſp'</hi>s <hi>Works,</hi> defended and maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I ſhall be the more conciſe in my juſt Remarks upon this our <hi>Maſquerading Stage-Player,</hi> as not being willing <hi>actum agere:</hi> Only I would deſire thee to conſider theſe few Heads:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the preſent Controverſie lies not between <hi>Proteſtant</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> in the general as ſuch, <hi>i. e. Church of England-Man, Presbyterian, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational,</hi> or <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> either as to Forms of Worſhip, or Modes of Diſcipline and their different perſwaſions therein; neither doth it primarily or poſitively,
<pb facs="tcp:51623:3"/> conſiſt in the order of <hi>God's Diſpenſation</hi> in the <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> for herein many upright Souls may unexitially be miſtaken, (though this be the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfuge our Adverſaries moſt miſerably betake themſelves unto, to amuſe both their Readers and Hearers with) but whether indeed there be ſuch a <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> as is mainly conſtitutive of a <hi>Repreſentative Headſhip,</hi> in a pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>per, and not barely and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lely a Political Senſe, together with an actual, real Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation, in an external Juridical Acceptation of Sin and Righteouſneſs between Chriſt and the Fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct, not by Infuſion but Imputation. This is that they would under their g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngling Pretences of the Merits of Chriſt, Holineſs, Duties and Works, rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve out of the way; which when done, <hi>Farewel Reformation,</hi> and the Covenant it ſelf to Beet; for by this they abſolutely condemn our Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> and exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe us juſtly to the Charge of <hi>Shifm</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> and ſtabilitate <hi>the Council of Trent:</hi> Nay, I dare confidently aſſert and can make it evidently appear, that there is never a Jeſuit in the World but might unequivocally, and that ſafely, as well as gladly, and round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly would, if requeſted thereunto, ſubſcribe unto their Treatiſes: Wherefore,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Note,</hi> That when-ever theſe our ſelf-Juſtificaries ſpeak moſtly of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin of Juſtification, and therein would expreſs themſelves by the Prepoſition <hi> [in]</hi> but <hi>[for]</hi> or <hi>[by]</hi> as knowing that the two latter are more capable in the Letter, tho' not in the leaſt, as to the Analogy of Faith, of a remoter Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, as to a Cauſality in the ſame, and conſequently becomes a more adap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſuitable, and undiſcerned retirement to lodge their rotten Hypotheſis in; hence it is alſo that their revived <hi>Cerberus</hi>'s Head, dogmatically aſſerts, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any manner of proof, or ſo much as once offering at the ſame. <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> D. Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liams<hi>'s Defence of Goſpel-Truth,</hi> p. 3.</note> 
               <q>That Merit and Matter in Judicial Acts or the ſame; which is a poſitive Falſhood, either as to their identick or eſſential Coincidence, or their more proper and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>inct uſes, and Applications, tho' here<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n their wicked retiring holes do lye.</q> Thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ing them into a convertibility of terms, they think to ſecure themſelves as much as may be from othe Obſervations of others; whereas in their Teaching<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings they abſolutely contradict their own Aſſertion, by ſeparating between Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Matter in our Juſtification, as that they take Merit of Chriſt's Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, from the Matter of the ſame, which as they ſay abides in him, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it to the matter of our own Righteouſneſs, the former being in Chriſt, the latter in us; which indeed is but our <hi>Juſtifaction,</hi> not <hi>Juſtification,</hi> by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the ſame; therefore thou wilt find, by a diligent attendance upon their Treatiſes in the whole ſcope and deſign of them, that they allow unto Chriſt but a meer Adjunctive ſtation unto the <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> or to be but a by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtander, and Looker on upon poor Sinners: That as they come in by Faith and Repen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance (notwithſtanding their acknowledging that it is by his Merits and Spirit) then it is that he ſteps in to apply a promiſe; and that as they continue in the ſame, ſo continues he in the diſcharge of this his <hi>Neonomian</hi> Office, as by them aſſigned unto him. Whence it genuinly follows:</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb facs="tcp:51623:3"/> 3. That their exploding of Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi> for an <hi>Antinomian,</hi> and exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſing him as One that is an Enemy to, and Rejecter of Graces, Duties, and good Works, an Eſpouſer of Sin, as diſowning of any Evil to be therein, ariſes from his not acknowledging of ſome cauſally-conditional (th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ugh not meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, with all our Adverſaries blinding Arts) Prerequiſites to our <hi>Juſtification;</hi> which had he done, he muſt have openly defied, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 5.and many more Texts that I could name, to the abſolute overthrow of the whole <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of the Covenant of Grace; but that in an acquitted and Righteous ſenſe, must be not only through, but as being choſen in Christ, and thereby in time made actual Members of that Myſtical Head, and that from, and by vertue of this our Fountain Union with him in <hi>Election,</hi> vertually by <hi>Redemption,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtatively by <hi>Effectual Calling,</hi> both the Change of our Natures is wrought, and conſequently the performance of our Duties, become exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rimentally unto us, acceptable with God. From a neglect of a due Conſideration of the foregoing Heads. I muſt tell thee, and that from my own Experience and Knowledge;</p>
            <p>That of all the Perſons in the World, that I have been acquainted with, eſpecial <hi> Profeſſors,</hi> either in their Polemical Writings, Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lary Argumenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or all Conferenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s; I never met with (I ſpeak not of any of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer perſwaſions, whereby they are diſtinguiſhed as ſuch, as being ſatisfied, that there are many truly worthy of each of them) a more prevaricating, incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent, falſe dealing, and vain glorious people, than ſuch as are ſettled and fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon this <hi>Neononomian</hi> bottom, and that as a Judgment of God, reſting upon them for their abuſe of his Righteouſneſs, ſo as to make it truckle thereunto in the bare Merits of the ſame, and become thereby a meer Drudge to our own Righteouſneſs, or the Righteouſneſs of the Spirit wrought within us which doth not only cast us the Foundation, but brings alſo a diſorder into the proper, pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Acts of the Trinity it ſelf, in their poſitively diſtinct perſonal Operations, wherein and whereby the Scripture evidently declares (Maugre all the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian</hi> and <hi>Arminian Quodammodo</hi>'s) the perfect Exaltation, Glory and Renown of one Eternal Deity, in the ſubſervient, regular, and conj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ynt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of that Covenant, which theſe perſons would overthrow) as carried on by theſe threee bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſed Subſiſtenci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, though eſſentially One; for the Father properly ſerves not the Son herein, nor the Son the Spirit, though each unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſly carry on the ſame deſign, yet it is by a diſtinct Demonſtration and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of both the form and matter of the ſame, as Graciouſly engaged in and by their own voluntary and everlaſting Counſels. Hence it is that the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> of old fell ſhort of their <hi>Juſtification,</hi> notwithſtanding their owning of the Grace of God, and their great Expectations from the ſame, in order unto it, <hi> Luk. 18. 81. &amp;c.</hi> and which is remarkable in reference unto <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf; who when he began to warp in this point, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. He is treated with, as no leſs than a Diſſembler, and all thoſe ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ding with him to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Power and Prevalency of Diſſimulation for a time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The reaſon of
<pb facs="tcp:51623:4"/> God's Jealouſie herein, and conſequently his Judgment upon them is very plain, in that it is the ſame Righteouſneſs in God, that he will have exalted both in the Salvation and Damnation of a Sinner, and that as exerted by, and held forth in the the Law, though towards the latter immediately, but to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer in, and <hi>[mediately]</hi> through Chriſt, and that not as to the meer Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects thereof, though they follow thereupon, but the ſolid ſubſtantial Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and Application of the ſame, as the ſtabilitating Ground and Juridical Foundation of both their Bliſs and Miſery, together with the juſt Proceedings of God therein. <hi>Mark Rom.</hi> 3. 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9. For it is the ſelf-ſame Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, under the juſt proſecuting Sentence and Charge whereof the Damned lie, in which it is that the Elect ſtand juſtify'd before God. Thus the ſame Doctrin preached by the ſame <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> became the Savour of Life, unto ſome, and the Savour of Death unto Death, unto others, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 15, 16. comp. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 3, 4. Therefore of Grace; for why ſhould any one be made Parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of that unto his Salvation, which pronounces a just Sentence of Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon another, but that it is meerly of Grace? The one standing justified in that which paſſes a Sentence of Condemnation upon the other. <hi>He that hath Ears to hear, let him hear.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51623:4"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A SHORT REVIEW OF SOME REFLECTIONS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN all Buildings, the Foundation is to be firſt ſecured; for where that is laid eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially and entirely in an Error, it is abſolutely impoſſible to be true unto it in an erected Fabrick upon the ſame, without a continued Superſtructure of Errors, <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacium mendaciis tegit, nè perfluat;</hi> for as Truth cannot be retained, and defended but by Truth, there being an inſeparable connexion between that of the loweſt, and higheſt Degree and Station thereof in the <hi>Church of God,</hi> as there was of every Nail and Thred of a Fringe in the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> to the <hi>Prieſt, Altar,</hi> and <hi>Sacrifice;</hi> ſo neither can Error be juſtly maintained, and genuinely pleaded for, but by a conſtant Enumeration of Errors, (thoſe being a <hi>decorum</hi> and order, even in <hi>Romances,</hi> and <hi>Play Books,</hi> as well as other things.) Hence it is that theſe two things do infallibly fall out, eſpecially in days of more than ordinary Tryals; when <hi>the Lord Jeſus comes with his Fan in his Hand,</hi> by this or the other Providence, <hi>thorowly to purge his Floor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. That the more the <hi>Heretick,</hi> properly ſuch (which I take to be one that either removes or perverts the Foundation that God hath laid) is put upon the defenſative part of his Error, he ſtill adhering unto the ſame, though never ſo latent at firſt, or for a while, and conſequently undiſcerned, the more ſpeedily and clearly, both he, and it will appear unto others. This is evident beyond all manner of Diſpute in our <hi>Neo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomian Conteſtors</hi> this day, as will fully appear anon.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That many who may ſeem to differ much, even to a direct oppoſition, as to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance at leaſt in ſeveral Circumſtantials, and more Minute Appendixes unto Truth, as ariſing either from their Darkneſs, and conſequently invincible miſtakes, in apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another, their peculiar mode of expreſſing themſelves, or their timing of each par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Truth, in aſſigning unto it its proper and more individual ſtation, order, uſe, and dependance; yet theſe as truly holding the Head, eſpecially in reference to <hi>the Doctrin of Juſtification</hi> (the Controverted point this day) whatever their preſent Diſſonancy, and thereupon Exaſperations may be, as between <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> will ſooner or later coaleſce, and fall into <hi>One,</hi> as being truly Members of the ſame Myſtical Body, becauſe the Foundation is the ſame, on which they are both laid and built. This will evidently appear from its contrary; and that, as relating unto the apparent <hi>Apoſtacies</hi> that have diſcovered themſelves in the Treatiſes of ſome later, as well as former Writers; who notwithſtanding their Vigour againſt the <hi>Papacy,</hi> even to a Preparation for its Burial by a winding-ſheet, yet upon trial of them in the Fundamental Points (which we muſt ſtick unto, or we not only loſe all, but eaſt a moſt wretched Aſperſion upon the Providences of God, and vindicate the Proceeding of our Enemies in the Death of the Martyrs) of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51623:5"/> have been driven to ſhelter themſelves under its argumentative Umbrage, and to draw forth the Arrows of their Defence out of it Quiver; yea, and as it is too noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly known to aſſign in a manner unto it from <hi>Proteſtaniſm,</hi> in the general the very right Hand of Fellowſhip in <hi>Chriſtoanity;</hi> and all becauſe the bottom is the ſame, on which they are fixed both in their Hopes and Truſt, it being natural for every thing to incline to its deſigned, and as ſuch proper and uniting Center. <hi>Jo.</hi> 5. 40. comp. <hi>ch.</hi> 6. 64, 65, 68, 69. <hi>Hinc illae lachrymae!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The matter and truth in Controverſie, having been by others ſo juſtly and fully ſtated and defended, we may be the more brief with this our blank Author, eſpecially, conſidering how weak, as well as falſe, his Attempts are againſt the ſame.</p>
               <p>His confident and grave <hi>Trumpeter</hi> tells us in the Preface, <hi>That the wrath of Man works not the Righteouſneſs of God;</hi> much leſs I am ſure doth our Author's lurking, and yet open Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks, with their falſe Reſerves, contribute in the leaſt to the Manifeſtation of the ſame, wherewith his Pamphlet is ſufficiently ſtuffed; for as <hi>Wrath</hi> is the reſultive Operation of <hi>Anger,</hi> which <hi>Anger is a Paſſion, created in the Soul by God himſelf, and drawn forth into its proper exerciſe by him into</hi> that which the Scripture calls <hi>Zeal for his Glory;</hi> ſo alſo is <hi>Politi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciſm in Man, a meer exurgency from</hi> that <hi>reaſoning faculty within him,</hi> by which he is diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed as well as by others of his Qualifications from the Beaſts that periſh; but all theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re diſcriminatively adjudged as to their ſinful or gracious poſition, frame, or operation, ae they co-work with, or for, or againſt the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> and that as to their principles and ends, the very Text our <hi>Prefacer</hi> produces, ſufficiently Demonſtrates the ſame. 1 <hi>Sams</hi> 2. 13. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 18. 27. 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 3. 13, 14. <hi>ch.</hi> 1. 10. <hi>Luk.</hi> 9. 54, 55. <hi>Judg.</hi> 5. 23. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 26. <hi>Ab equis, ad aſinos.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Author</hi> in his <hi>firſt,</hi> and part of the <hi>ſecond page,</hi> highly commends (after a little vent of his Gall) Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi>'s <hi>Sermons,</hi> and that for ſome certain uſes and ends that he is pleaſed to aſſign unto them: That he exalts Free-Grace, Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, his Paths, in expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the aſtoniſhing love of Jeſus, and that in the Redemption of Mankind, how Mercy and Truth, Righteouſneſs and Peace met, and kiſſed each other in him, that Juſtice and Goodneſs had their equal diſcovery in his ſatisfaction, and how that he depreſſes good Works and holy Duties, (but obſerve how he takes him, <hi>p.</hi> 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as to ſatisfying God's Juſtice, or meriting any thing for us. Here the hooks lies) from being <hi>ingredieats</hi> of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> and ſo on. I doubt this word <hi>irgredients</hi> will prove but a very naſty one, by then we have compared it with his ten charges againſt the Doctor; but for all this we muſt endeavour as inoffenſively and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly as we can to reſcue him out of his Hands, for I never iiked <hi>ovem lupo committere,</hi> or <hi>Agninis lactibus canem alligare,</hi> ſince we ſee <hi>our Author</hi> hath no ſooner got him into his clut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, by his fawning reſerved acknowledgments, but like the Lyon in the Fable, tears him to pieces.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Some few things to be remarked out of our Author,</hi> p. 2, 3, 4. <hi>before we enter preciſely upon his Decemvir'd Charge againſt the Doctor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. His inconſiſtency, even whilſt he endeavours falſly to charge the <hi>Doctor</hi> wirh the ſame (beſides, as we ſhall ſee in the Cloſe of his Treatiſe how he overthrows the whole of his Forgery, and that even with his own Pen unto our Hands) from comparing what he ſays, <hi>p.</hi> 2, 3, and 4. and ſeveral other places, with what <hi>his Armour-bearer</hi> in the Preface expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: <q>Far be it from me to cenſure or arraign the <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> (note thoſe words <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Spirit)</hi> of the Reverend Dr. <hi>Criſp, whoſe Soul I take to be in Heaven,</hi> and whoſe Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Deſigns might be ſincere and good, though not ſo diſtinctly ſee the nature, order, and mutual Rela<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ions and Dependencies, to and upon each other. <hi>Pref. l.</hi> 17, 22. <hi>Author, p.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. His Zeal for Chriſt's imputed Righteouſneſs, makes him vilifie, and <hi>almoſt,</hi> (mark that word) exclude an inherent Righteouſneſs of our own; comp. <hi>p.</hi> 3. Though the Author of theſe Sermons often attempts to perſwade you thas he is no <hi>Antinomian, i. e.</hi> that he is not againſt the Law of Righteouſneſs and Holineſs; that he is no diſcourager of of Faith and good Works, and the ſeveral Duties of Religion; yet nothing is more evident than this, that he is <hi>a profeſſed Enemy to theſe,</hi> and uſeth all the Art he can to make others ſo.</q> Suit but theſe together, and thou wilt find a Preliminary Tranſcript of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51623:5"/> both his Treachery and I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>conſiſtency, wherewith we ſhall be ſufficiently glutted anon; beſides <hi>p.</hi> 58. He makes him a Derider of the new Birth, with many other falſe, as well as bitter Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſms, which ſhould they be but in the Hundredth part of them true, <hi>would abſolutely beſpeak the Doctor a Reprobate,</hi> Gal. 4. 29, 30. Scarce one, or but very few of his Stigmatizing marks, if Faith in its Analogy be attended unto, that can be reckoned of the ſpots of God's Children.</p>
               <p n="2">2. HIS Diſpleaſure againſt him for ſeparating between Juſtification and Sanctification, which the Holy Scriptures <hi>(as he ſays)</hi> always joyn together, <hi>p.</hi> 3. but not as to the ends for which <hi>our Author and his Jeſuitical Fraternity</hi> would have them promiſcuouſly jumbled together; does the Scripture joyn them, and in no other a Senſe doth the <hi>Doctor</hi> ſeparate them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. HIS ſolemn Appeal unto the <hi>Searcher of Hearts,</hi> before he enters upon this his allowed, deliberate, and ſtudied falſe Dealings with the <hi>Doctor,</hi> of his Innocence in the ſame, I could tell him of the like Attempt of another, with whom God hath met in the very Language of his Imprecation. Let him and ſuch remember <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>BUT to the charges themſelves: Or, <hi>ab equis ad aſinos,</hi> from bad to worſe: But, before we proceed, note, <hi>Reader,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THAT there is not one Charge of the whole ten that <hi>our Author</hi> produces againſt the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor,</hi> wherein he may be ſaid to have done him the leaſt piece of Juſtice, or to deal equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably with him according to the matter he hath in Hand, and that in the very literal De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant Conſtruction of the ſame which, if otherwiſe thou findeſt upon an unequivocal, plain, and candid comparing of the <hi>Doctor,</hi> with his <hi>Traducer,</hi> and that according to the pure ſimplicity of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> I will lay my Head under thy Feet, to be trampled into Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. And this, without any manner of reſerves, (God aſſiſting) I ſhall nakedly clear up unto thee; therefore look to it that thou be not deceived herein, either by the <hi>Author;</hi> or any other, <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 29. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 21. <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 11. for herein I muſt declare my Judgment, leaving thee to thine own, and am ready to make it good at any time, that the whole of what I have yet ſeen in Print againſt Dr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> take it in the full matter, and compacted deſign thereof, will no more avail, in order unto thy Salvation, than the <hi>Turkiſh Alcoran</hi> it ſelf would: Nay further, ſhould any one be ſaved upon the Principles urged, tho' hut tacitly, and ſomewhat obſcurely for the preſent, by theſe (to ſay, the beſt of them) <hi>Semi-juſticia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Rom.</hi> 9. 31, 32. his Hallelujahs in Heaven, as genuinly ſpringing from ſuch a root, would be but meer Hypocriſie, ſufficiently ſeaſoned with a Proud, Phariſaical, and vain-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Spirit, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18. 11. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This I tell thee again and again, I will be bound to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. And as I would beg no Man's Vote or Subſcription to the work that lies before me, as one that deſigned to catch or enſnare Souls from an appearance of Numbers and Names, <hi>one of</hi> Bellarmine<hi>'s</hi> 15 <hi>marks of a true Church;</hi> ſo neither would I conceal my ſelf as one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious of a vile undertaking: But that which is moſt lamentable, and calls for pity in our <hi>Author,</hi> as not far diſtant from the unpardonable Sin it ſelf, if I underſtand any thing of the Word of God, is, His deliberate, contrived, and conſequently approv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Actings againſt his own Light, (as with rhe <hi>Jews</hi> of old; who, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Three things concur to the making up of the Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt:</hi> 1. <hi>Light in the Mind.</hi> 2. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice in the Heart.</hi> 3: <hi>The Inſenſibleneſs of the Sin. Mr.</hi> Dod<hi>'s</hi> firſt Sheet, and 27th. Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> though the Matter of Fact, in the Miracles our Saviour wrought was plain, naked, and ſo convincingly open before them, that they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves could not gainſay, yet ſuch was their Malice againſt the truth, that they would rather aſcribe the power which they were wrought unto <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> than the Finger of God) for there is ſcarce any one of his Charges againſt the <hi>Doctor,</hi> but evidently demonſtrates, if the place be view'd, that his confutation lay before his Eyes, even then when he was picking the Matter thereof out of his Works: Therefore thou wilt find, that when-ever he is forced to own or Subſcribe unto ſome things, as being Truths in the <hi>Doctor's Treatiſe,</hi> he endeavours thereby to blaſt his Reputation, without any manner of Proof, as confidently aſſigning unto the whole of his Labours, but a more crafty fetch, ridiculing of the Goſpel, and all to deceive the People, with ſeveral ſuch dogmatical Aſſertions, without any juſt demonſtration, mix'd with ſome Theatrical Flouriſhes, ſo far from having in them any Savour of Grace, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51623:6"/> of truth; that indeed there is not ſo much as the leaſt Tincture o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> common-Morality in the whole Scope of this his pitiful Pamphlet, wherein h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> barking or canine keenneſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 59. 6, 7. is far more acceptable than all his fawning Treacheries, by which he would uſher in his peſtilent, both <hi>Antinomian,</hi> as well as <hi>Neonomian Hereſies.</hi> I muſt confeſs that the ſhaking of my Dog's Tail is more pleaſing, as having more of Sincerity in it, than the whole of his introductory Sycophancy to this his Treatiſe.</p>
               <p>For the Proof of which, we ſhall conſider our <hi>Author</hi>'s firſt Charge, to begin withal.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He tells us, <hi>Page</hi> 4. That, <hi>the Doctor will not aſcribe unto Faith that which the Apoſtle</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aul <hi>ſo often doth, in our Juſtification before God:</hi> and withal, <hi>that under a pretence of exalting Chriſt,</hi> (to omit the reſt of his pitiful, wyre-drawn, and forced Sophiſms) <hi>he denies that we are juſtified by Faith in Chriſt—</hi>Take a View <hi>(Reader)</hi> of his falſe Treachery herein, and therein judge, who it is (though our <hi>Author</hi> would impudently fix it upon the <hi>Doctor)</hi> that truly ſtumbles at the Threſhold, whether the Traduced, or his Accuſer. The <hi>Doctor,</hi> p. 98. (whence our <hi>Author</hi> curtails his partial Quotation againſt him) diſtinguiſhes between a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive and active recipiency of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> (which indeed, if truly weighed, is the very plague, as well as Teſt, of an <hi>Arminian.</hi> This Diſcrimination, and the <hi>Doctors,</hi> manifeſt literal and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed deſign therein, had our <hi>Author</hi> but honeſtly attended unto, and juſtly repreſented to his <hi>Reader,</hi> he knew would have abſolutely overthrown the whole of his undertaking, ſubverted him in the very Grounds of his Proceedings againſt him, and unvail'd him of all his forged ſeemingly colourable pretences, whereon, and wherein he conſtantly fixes and ſhades himſelf in the vileneſs of his Charge againſt him, and thereupon miſerably concludes, <hi>that a Man may have a part in Chriſt, either without, or deſtitute of Faith,</hi> (i. e.) living and dying in unbelief. But Sir <hi>Ignoto Author,</hi> or <hi>Knight of the Poſt</hi> rather, know this, that we muſt not be run down with bantering Impudence, empty Flouriſhes, much leſs forged Accuſation, but expect both our Information and Eſtabliſhment, from clear and undeniable Demonſtrations, back'd and fortified with ſolid and well-quadrated Scripture-proofs. And this the <hi>Dr.</hi> doth immediately in the following Page, 99. from <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. 18, 19. which our <hi>Author</hi> takes no notice of, though it at the very time of this his Forgery, look'd, yea, ſtared him fully in the Face. The ſumm and ſubſtance whereof is this, <hi>That</hi> Ephraim <hi>muſt be turned, before ſhe can turn unto the Lord; That ſhe never reflected upon her ſelf, till after her converſion.</hi> And doth not this beſpeak a paſſive part ſhe had in the Lord, or a pre-poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing Act of God in her Soul, before ſhe could in the leaſt put forth an active recipiency of him? And doth not the latter abſolutely depend upon the former? Is not this alſo the Judgment of the <hi>Aſſemblies? Cha.</hi> 10: <hi>Art.</hi> 2. <q>This effectual Call is of God's free and ſpecial Grace alone, not from any thing at all foreſeen in Man, who is <hi>altogether Paſſive therein,</hi> until being quickned, and renewed by the Holy Spirit, he is thereby ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to anſwer <hi>this call,</hi> and to embrace the Grace offered and conveyed in it.</q> This the <hi>Doctor</hi> furthet proves, <hi>Ibid.</hi> from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. 3. where he tells us, <q>Hence it is that the entrance of <hi>Chriſt</hi> into a Perſon, is attributed unto the Power of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the Power of the Lord muſt come over a Perſon before <hi>Chriſt</hi> can have a poſſeſſion of that Perſon, (and then gives this reaſon) in regard of the croſneſs of the Spirit of Man, to the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> when <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath once revealed himſelf, and made the Soul behold his Beauty, and acquainted the Soul with his Excellency, then the Soul begins to embrace him, <hi>(mark that, Reader)</hi> and to hold him faſt, and will not let him go.</q>Doth the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> now exclude Faith in the Apoſtle's Senſe? Or rather doth he not aſſign to it, its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per place, according unto, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 48. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 15, 16. This Orthodoxy, (though nauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to our <hi>Authors Arminian</hi> Palate, and which puts him upon ſo many miſerable ſhifts, may be proved and cleared from ſeveral exemplary Inſtances in Scripture, as well as poſitively Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinal points in the ſame; for it is not the moſt Gracious Internal Actings of the Soul, tho' wrought and maintained of God himſelf, that works a Change in our perſonal Covenant-State; conſider it well, <hi>(Reader)</hi> and weigh it in the ballances of the Sanctuary, and that without reſpect of Perſons or Parties; for as God's Act in Juſtification is purely Forenſick, and therein reſpects our Perſons, and depends not in the leaſt upon his Phyſical Operation, which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51623:6"/> is entirely regenerative, whoſe ſubject therein properly is our Natures; ſo alſo neither doth our part in him in the act of Converſion it ſelf, depend upon our actual cloſing with him, any further than our paſſive recipiency of him makes way for the ſame, both in its productive cauſe, and continued, irreſiſtible, and yet Gracious complying Deſigns. This is clear from <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 12. wherein a paſſive Reception of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is that which precedes an active one. See alſo 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 10, 19 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65. 1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 16. comp. <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>ch.</hi> 1. 48, 49. 50. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 6. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. 60, 61, 62, 63. Thus it was with <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am,</hi> the <hi>Proto-Applicatory Subject</hi> of this Grace, after his fall. How did the Lord deal with him, in order to his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery? Did he wait for an actual Exhibition of his Faith to juſtifie him for the ſame? Nay, did he not rather purſue him, when Rebelliouſly, under the obſtinate Fruits, and reigning Effects of his (and ours in him) <hi>Federal Act of Apoſtacy?</hi> But with what? even a promiſe. But what was this promiſe? the Seed of the Woman. And what was this Seed in the root, or primary Acceptation of it? I ſuppoſe, <hi>Chriſt,</hi> (which is evident in <hi>Eve</hi>'s miſtake, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. 1. beſides many other undeniable Scriptural poſitive Proofs) therefore reckoned upon as <hi>the firſt Born, firſt Fruits, yea, firſt Gift,</hi> and <hi>to have the Preheminence in all things,</hi> before even Faith, or any other work of the Spirit, which is fully expreſſive of not only the nature as to the matter, but executive form it ſelf of the Covenant of Grace, which Covenant conſiſts of Promiſes, or, as Dr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> ſays, <hi>That the Covenant of Grace, is, Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction-purpoſes and decrees wrapt up in promiſes:</hi> But what are theſe promiſes? <hi>Mr.</hi> Strong, <hi>in his Treatiſe of the Covenants,</hi> tells us, <hi>That they conſiſt not only of two kinds,</hi> viz. <hi>perſonal and real, but that the former takes place in the adminiſtration of the ſame from the latter.</hi> If ſo, then our Doctor is right; that Chriſt is not only the <hi>firſt Gift,</hi> but that until we receive him in a paſſive Senſe, how can he be unto us the Finiſher, much leſs the Author of our Faith? And 'tis true, that God convinces our firſt Parents of their ſin, and therein begins with <hi>Adam,</hi> which is ſomewhat remarkable, though <hi>Eve</hi> was firſt in the Tranſgreſſion, yet choſe rather to deal with the former, as that in and by <hi>him, as a Repreſentative Head,</hi> he dealt with all his poſterity. But what is the Fruit of all his convincing, though juſt Proceedings againſt him? Nothing but a continued act of Rebellion, and that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the mild Proceedings of the Lord with him, even in the cool of the Evening, not ſo much as a bare acknowledgment of a matter of Fact in a Tranſgreſſive Senſe, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an aggravating of the ſame, by their (or our firſt Parents) ultimate, tho' tacit, caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the cauſe thereof upon God, rather than themſelves. Which way doth the Lord take to reſtore them, or to bring them to himſelf? It is evident, by the application of a promiſe, and that under a <hi>perſonal</hi> Conſideration, before any of that which betokens a real one, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 15. <hi>comp. v.</hi> 21. The Perſon included in the promiſe, they firſt receive, and thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Cloathing or Juſtifying Garment, <hi>typified</hi> in the <hi>Coats of Skins,</hi> which were made, or wrought out, and alſo truly applied by the Lord himſelf, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 23, 24, 25, 26: Thus it was with <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, who had a paſſive part in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> (I ſpeak it not of that which is barely decretive, or redemptive) even before his actual cloſing with him, <hi>Act.</hi> 9. 3, 4, 5. <hi>comp. v.</hi> 6. And is not this Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi>'s Doctrin, in his diſtinguiſhing between a paſſive, and active recipiency of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> namely, That God, out of his Bowels of Pity and Mercy, will reach out his Chriſt to thoſe that have no Hands to receive him, no Faith to believe in him, but are rather as froward Patients, ſhutting their Teeth againſt their Remedy: And is not this evident, without the leaſt reſerve in the caſe of <hi>Paul,</hi> as well as that of <hi>Adam?</hi> as that the part the Elect have in him, in a convertive Senſe, proceeds primarily from a paſſive Application of them unto their Souls, as precedaneous unto their actual knowing, and voluntary cloſing with him, <hi>Act.</hi> 22. 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8. Nay, take it in the moſt gentle of God's Proceedings with his Adult Elect in the Act of Converſion, or his bringing them over by Faith unto himſelf, they are primarily paſſive herein. Conſult for an inſtance but the caſe of <hi>Lydia,</hi> and the Lord's dealing with her Soul, <hi>Act.</hi> 16. wherein it was evident that her Faith was the Fruit of Union, or that ſhe had a paſſive part in the Lord (beſides that of a decretive, and ſo a Fountain one; and that of a redeemed, purchaſed, and ſo a truly virtual one) before ſhe actually cloſed with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51623:7"/> him in the recipiency of Faith, properly ſo; for it is well known, though Faith be the inſtrumental cauſe, yet that it is the Spirit that is perſonally, and ſo peculiarly the effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cauſe of our Juſtification, and that not by an infuſion of qualities, but poſitive, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Application of that Righteouſneſs (as being his voluntary, gracious undertaken Office) whereof, and wherein he makes it not only to appear, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, but material cauſe of the ſame, and that not by the Mediums of Graces, as Mediator only, but the ſolid actual Obedience of him, who on that very account be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came their <hi>Repreſentative Head,</hi> Joh. 16. 13, 14. <hi>comp.</hi> Rom. 5. 19. And though none of theſe ſtand aſunder in the compleat uniting, as well as operative, and conſequently Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Act of our Juſtification, but to ſay or ſuppoſe that the two former are not ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent unto, and do not wholly depend upon the latter, and that as to the very eſſence of our juſtified State, as well as Order, is at one blow to build and eſtabliſh the <hi>Covenant of Grace</hi> upon that of Works, and thereby to aſſign ſuch a <hi>CA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SA SINE Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>A NON,</hi> unto our believing (as our <hi>Author</hi> very cloſely infers <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 30, 31, 32, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that Faith is not ſo much a Manifeſtation as an entitling Grace, and what that means, we know very well) that the whole Myſteries of the Goſpel, in Election, Redemption; yea, and Vocation alſo in the effectual Application of them both, as to imputation on the one Hand, and Inhaeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the other unto a Sinner, muſt attend upon our Faith, and that as the antecedent Faederal (but not meritorious by any means, though perhaps, <hi>STILO NEONOMIANENSI, acquiſititious)</hi> condition of all the benefits, both deſigned by, and received from them. This is evident, I ſay, in the Example of <hi>Lydia.</hi> That the Lord opened her Heart, is too notorious to be denied, and that this opening of her Heart is expreſs'd and clear'd up from the Fruit thereof, even her Attendance upon what <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake, which was no more than the hearing of Faith; it was <hi>Faith upon this opening</hi> that cauſed her to liſten: Now, is it not as evident a Demonſtration of <hi>Irrationality in Logick,</hi> as it is of <hi>Hereſie</hi> in <hi>Divinity,</hi> if we do but attend unto the Analogy of the <hi>Covenant of Grace, ut priùs,</hi> in all the parts thereof, and that, both of perſonal as well as real promiſes, the latter depending upon the former: That ſhe ſhould either have her Heart opened by the Lord, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhe ſhould attend unto what the Lord by <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake unto her, and yet not to be pre-poſſeſſed of, or by the Lord, unto both this opening and attendance.</p>
               <p>TO deny this, is not only blockiſh Nonſenſe, but a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or, <hi>Man's ſelf-ability engaging againſt God.</hi> The <hi>Divinity,</hi> and therein Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gion and Practice of ſome in this our day, may in a more eſpecial manner, by way of alluſion, be obſerved from the proceeding of that wicked King <hi>Ahaz,</hi> 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 16. 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15. Who, tho' after the ſight of the <hi>Altar</hi> at <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> and his thereupon bringing it in the exactly, made formative frame, and material fixing of it in the Houſe of the Lord; yet removed not the <hi>Altar of the Lord wholly</hi> out of the Houſe, but diſplaced it, and that not as to render it entirely uſeleſs, or of no advantage unto him, but that under a colour of enquiring by it, he might the more pretextually, or covertly go on in the eſtabliſhing himſelf in his own ways of Works and Holineſs, as knowing that the Merits, or Worth of all his performances, did typically lye there; therefore a <hi>Brazen Altar,</hi> as acknowledged by himſelf. Thus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our <hi>Neonomian Hereſie,</hi> ſome allow unto Chriſt but an adjunctive ſtation (remote enough from the fixed deſign of God) unto the <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> as to the acceptance, both of our Perſons and Performances with the Lord, <hi>i. e.</hi> That as we perform this or the other duty, though therein we Sacrifice but to our own Nets, yet it is but running to <hi>this Altar,</hi> or the Merits thereof, by which we muſt enquire into, and come to know that our Works, and conſequently our own perſons become in a juſtifying Senſe approved by, or acceptable with him.</p>
               <p>From hence our <hi>Author, p.</hi> 5. lets fly his barking, or conciſionary Arrows againſt the <hi>Doctor,</hi> through the ſides of <hi>Beza,</hi> whoſe treatment is at beſt but tragi-comoedial, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther comoedially-tragical: Alaſs, poor <hi>Beza,</hi> who it ſeems in his Senſe is but <hi>a Pretender to mend Texts, nay, an Alterer of them, by Daring and Preſumptious Practices,</hi> inſtead of a juſt Explainer of them, as our <hi>Author</hi> acknowledges, though with a, <hi>perhaps,</hi> (as <hi>Hobs</hi> upon
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51623:7"/> his <hi>Atheiſtical</hi> Entrance into Eternity) <hi>it was the only conſiderable fault</hi> (more canino &amp; dogmatico,) <hi>in that worthy</hi> (by all means to Sugar the Pill) <hi>Man's Annotations.</hi> But however it ſeems, <hi>Beza</hi> muſt down, for in the judgment of our Scrutinous blind-Mans-buff he hath opened a Text of Scripture, that gives too great a Countenance to the <hi>Antinomian</hi> Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, which our <hi>Author</hi> is pleaſed very Learnedly to define by the Character of <hi>Criſpianiſm,</hi> and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntitle himſelf amongſt the number of the <hi>Criticks,</hi> as having <hi>unmask'd</hi> the ſame. The Text it ſeems is this, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 1. Therefore being juſtified, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore! Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? I ſuppoſe the Word is an <hi>Illative,</hi> and as it makes way for an Inference and Concluſion, ſo it abſolutely beſpeaks ſome <hi>undeniable Maxim</hi> or <hi>Tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h</hi> formerly fixed upon, without a reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which, it would prove but ſuperfluous and trifling, and indeed it is, that no leſs than which our <hi>Author,</hi> together with the reſt of his Tribe under a pretence of exalting Faith, would totally overthrow. The <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> having in the immediately foregoing <hi>verſe, chap.</hi> 4. 25. poſitively as well as incluſively declared, that in what <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative Head of the Elect did, lay their Juſtification before God, though the meer Act of God, in juſtifying is purely of <hi>Grace, Rom.</hi> 3. 24. yet conſidering that <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and that by the appointment of the Father, purſuant to the Eternal Counſels of his Will, and that according to their mutual engagements in the <hi>Everlaſting Covenant,</hi> became Incarnate, obey'd, ſuffer'd, yea, roſe again, and that not for himſelf, nor barely on the Behalf, and for the good of thoſe given unto him, but more immediately in their room and ſtead. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 14. It became juſt with God; and it is a juridical, as well as External Act in him, to reckon upon ſuch as juſtifi'd thereby and therein, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 25, 26. which Grace of Juſtification in the prefixed matter and form thereof, they enter upon through <hi>Chriſt</hi> by Faith, and all the Fruits of the ſame, ſuch as Peace with God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> otherwiſe this Text, <hi>ch.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 2. muſt be read thus,—<hi>By whom alſo we have acceſs b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Faith into this</hi> FAITH, inſtead of <hi>this Grace,</hi> which purely refers to Juſtification, as an Act, in, of, and by God himſelf) <hi>wherein we ſtand. Dr. Owen</hi> brings in <hi>Cyrillus Alexandri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us,</hi> in <hi>Joan.</hi> Lib. 11. Cap. 25. ſpeaking thus:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quaemadmodum praevaricatione primi hominis ut in primitiis generis noſtri, morti addicti fuimus; eodem modo</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Owen</hi>'s Treat. of Juſtification, p 482.</note> 
                     <hi>per obedientiam &amp; juſtitiam Chriſti, in quantum ſeipſum legi ſubjecit, quamvis legis author eſſet, benedictio &amp; vivificatio quae per Spiritum eſt, ad totam noſtram penetravit naturam.</hi> And <hi>Leo. Epiſt.</hi> 12. <hi>ad Juvenalem. ut autem repararet omnium vitam, recepit omnium cauſam; ut ſicut per unius reatum omnes facti fuerunt peccatores, ità per unius innocentiam omnes fuerunt innocentes; inde in homines manaret juſtitia, ubi eſt humana ſuſcepta natura.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again, This is the cleareſt Teſtimony, that what the Lord Chriſt did and ſuſtered was for us, and not for himſelf. For without the <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Owen<hi>'s Treat. of Juſtification,</hi> p. 287.</note> conſideration hereof, all the Obedience which he yielded unto the Law, might be lookt on as due only on his Account, and himſelf to have been ſuch a Saviour as the <hi>Socinians imagine,</hi> who ſhould <hi>do all with us from God,</hi> and nothing <hi>with God for us.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>And in his anſwer to Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> upon the ſame Charge of <hi>Antinomianiſm,</hi> and the Grounds thereof, that flies about our Ears this day; He ſays, <q>My ſecond is, that which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured for any one, thereunto he hath a right: The thing that is obtained, is granted by him, of whom it is obtained, and that to them, for whom it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. To this is anſwered, 1. In the Margent, that I ſhould make <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Appendix to</hi> Dr. Owen<hi>'s Anſwer to</hi> Biddle, <hi>p.</hi> 35.</note> great Changes in <hi>England,</hi> if I could make all the Lawyers believe this ſtrange Doctrine; but of what the Lawyers believe, or do not believe, Mr. <hi>B.</hi> is no Competent Judge, be it ſpoken without Diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for the Law is not his ſtudy: I, who (perhaps) have much leſs skill than him ſelf; will be bound at any time to give him Twenty Caſes, out of the Civil and Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non Law, to make good this Aſſertion; which if he knows not, that it may be done, he ought not to ſpeak with ſuch Confidence of theſe things. Nay, amongſt our own Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, (whom perhaps he intends) I am ſure I may be informed, that, if a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercede with another, to ſettle his Land by conveyance to a third Perſon, giving him
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51623:8"/> that Conveyance to keep in truſt until the time come, that he ſhould by the Intention of the Conveyer enjoy the Land, though he, for whom it is granted, have not the leaſt knowledge of it, yet he hath ſuch a Right unto the Land thereby created, as cannot be diſanull'd.</q> This is the very thing for which it is that <hi>Dr. Criſp</hi> brings in this Text, and <hi>Beza</hi>'s Annotation thereupon, and that in the very Page, whence the Charge is fetcht. Namely, that, <q>Juſtification is truly and properly the work of God himſelf, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the work of Faith. Nay, he goes farther, Suppoſe <hi>(ſays he)</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Dr. Criſp's <hi>Works. Vol.</hi> 2. <hi>Pag.</hi> 325.</note> you ſhould have the words to run as they are commonly render'd.I anſwer, Then are we to diſtinguiſh in Faith of two things; there is the <hi>Act</hi> it ſelf of believing, and the <hi>Object</hi> on which we do believe; and ſo the words may be underſtood thus: <hi>Being juſtified</hi> by the Righteouſneſs of Faith, or by the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which we do believe, <hi>We have Peace with God,</hi> and ſo aſcribe our Juſtification to the Object of our believing the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and not to the Act of Believing. The truth is, Beloved, the <hi>Act of Believing</hi> is a Work, and as much our Work as our Fear and Prayer, and love is; and the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſhould contradict himſelf, when he ſaith, <hi>We are ſaved by Grace, through Faith, not of Works,</hi> if he mean the Act of Faith: And he might as well have ſaid, <hi>We are not juſtified by Works, but we are juſtified by Works.</hi>
                  </q> This he further diſtinguiſhes in the ſame Page, unto which I refer thee (which our <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> with various huffing Reflections, and rotten Inferences, moſt partially and falſly quotes in his 6th and 7th Pages) That, to be ſhort, there is not only a diſtinction between the <hi>Act</hi> and <hi>Object</hi> of Faith, and that as properly relating unto our Juſtification and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs therein, but alſo to God's <hi>Act</hi> of our Juſtification in Heaven, as fully Precedaneous to the termination thereof in Conſcience. Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> upon the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 30. in his refutation of <hi>Socinus</hi> and <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> tells us, That <q>
                     <hi>Chriſt</hi> is made of God, Righteouſneſs unto us in <hi>ſuch a way and manner,</hi> as the nature of the thing doth require. Say ſome, it is, <hi>becauſe by him we are juſtified.</hi> However the Text ſays not, <hi>That by him we are juſtified,</hi> but he is of God <hi>made Righteouſneſs unto us,</hi> which is not our <note place="margin">Dr. Owen <hi>of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification,</hi> p. 502.</note> 
                     <hi>Juſtification,</hi> but the Ground, Cauſe and Reaſon, whereon we are juſtified. Righteouſneſs is one thing, and Juſtification is another.</q> Now either this Righteouſneſs is in an eternal, decretive, and material ſenſe, truly and irrevocably theirs, before they believe, or upon what Grounds is it that God can be reckoned juſt, in his juſtifying of them, even when they believe? But there is a ſecret grub lies at the bottom of all this our <hi>Author</hi>'s Indignation, which we muſt endeavour to find out. See Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> againſt Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> in the fore-mentioned Appendix. <q>Now I ſay, that in the ſenſe, wherein I affirm, that Juſtification is terminated in Conſcience, I may yet alſo affirm, and that ſuitably to the utmoſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Owen<hi>'s Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix againſt Mr.</hi> Baxter, <hi>in his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to</hi> Biddle. pag. 19.</note> of mine in that expreſſion, that Juſtification by Faith is not a knowledge or feeling of Juſtification before given, nor a Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in or by our own Conſciences, but ſomewhat that goes before all ſuch Juſtification as this is, and is a Juſtification before God.</q> And is not this true? How many ſcores of our ancient ſolid Reformers might be brought in to atteſt this truth, wherein and whereby they diſtinguiſh'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a Fundamental ſenſe, as <hi>Proteſtants</hi> from <hi>Papiſts?</hi> But it ſeems (as our <hi>Author</hi> thinks) Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi> did not pitch upon a right Text in this of <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 1. though it and its Context undeniably prove he did, to fix this his Diſcrimination upon, and therefore alters the Scene of the Charge againſt him, <hi>i, e.</hi> from a diſtinguiſhing to a confounding Explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>p.</hi> 7. where he, to his own Admiration, no doubt, Learnedly explains <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 24. for if the <hi>Apoſtle</hi>'s Senſe or Meaning be the ſame in one place of his <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> as well as in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when he ſpeaks more eſpecially of <hi>being juſtified by Faith,</hi> (which our <hi>Author</hi> firmly aſſerts) why then ſhould he make a diſtinction between the <hi>Act</hi> and <hi>Object</hi> of Faith, from <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 24. which he denies unto the ſame <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> from <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 1. in <hi>Beza</hi>'s Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s Quotation of him for that end? A ſtrong Memory I ſee is exceeding requiſite for a Lying and Prevaricating Spirit: This is not far unlike the <hi>Devil</hi>'s Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51623:8"/> with <hi>Job;</hi> who when he ſaw that his Accuſation of him before God for an Hypocrite, did not prove true, or hold Water, then does he ſlily ſeek by his Wife in an Inſtrumental Senſe to cauſe him to part with his Integrity. Juſt thus it is that our <hi>Author</hi> moſt ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſpews out his own Treachery. Dr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> upon <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 6. ſaith, that—<q>Our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is in God's Gifts, and in <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s perſonating of us, (mark this piece of <hi>Criſpianiſm)</hi> and apprehending of us; it is perfect and compleat, though in our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as in us, it is wrought by degrees. Further. <hi>pag.</hi> 218, 219. He <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Doct.</hi> Goodwin <hi>upon the Epiſtle to the</hi> Eph. <hi>ch.</hi> 2. 6. <hi>p.</hi> 217, 218. 219.</note> tells us, You ſee the diſtinction between <hi>in Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>with Chriſt;</hi> we are ſaid to be quickned <hi>with Chriſt;</hi> why? becauſe that Work, as it is wrought <hi>in Chriſt</hi> once for us, hath now ſome Accompliſhment in us; but ſpeaking of the Reſurrection to come, he does not ſay we are raiſed up <hi>in Chriſt,</hi> but raiſed up <hi>with Chriſt;</hi> do but learn to diſtinguiſh, for the want of this makes many Men to miſtake. A Man <hi>before he is called,</hi> he is <hi>juſtified in Chriſt,</hi> but not <hi>with Chriſt,</hi> that is, it is not <hi>actually applyed</hi> to the Man's Perſon; his Perſon is not put <hi>in foro verbi,</hi> in the State of Juſtification. Learn, I ſay, to diſtinguiſh between receiving a thing <hi>in Chriſt,</hi> and receiving it <hi>with Chriſt;</hi> you receive it <hi>with Chriſt</hi> when it is <hi>actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applyed</hi> to your Perſon; <hi>we now ſit together in Chriſt in Heaven,</hi> would you deſire no other ſitting in Heaven <hi>with Chriſt,</hi> than now you have? Certainly you would: As you ſit <hi>in Chriſt,</hi> ſo likewiſe you would ſit <hi>with Chriſt;</hi> ſo take a Man before ſuch time as he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth, and is converted to God, would he have no other Sanctification? Would you have for your Child, ſuppoſe you believe him to be elect, or had an immediate infallible War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, ſo to think, no other Sanctification or Juſtification than he hath then? No, you would have him Sanctified <hi>with Chriſt,</hi> and juſtified <hi>with Chriſt,</hi> which is to have that which he had <hi>in Chriſt,</hi> applyed to him; and he put actually in his own Perſon, in the ſtate of it. The want of the conſideration of theſe things, cauſeth a great miſtake in this Age; you ſhall find that ſtill the Scripture uſeth that Phraſe of theſe things, which we not only have <hi>in Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>in a common perſon,</hi> but it muſt be <hi>applied</hi> unto our own Perſons alſo; for would any Man deſire to be no more glorified than he is now? Yet as we are <hi>perfectly</hi> glorified <hi>in Chriſt</hi> now, ſo we were perfectly juſtified <hi>in Chriſt when he aroſe,</hi> and <hi>perfectly juſtified from all Eternity.</hi> Who ſhall condemn the Elect of God? Saith the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,</hi> Yet theſe muſt be applied to our own Perſons, and our Perſons muſt actually be put into this condition: When we come to Heaven, then he ſaith, <hi>we ſhall</hi> ſit <hi>with Chriſt</hi> in his Throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. but while we are here on Earth, then it is ſitting <hi>in Chriſt.</hi> The Conſideration of this diſtinction, would in a word clear the great Controverſie that is now between the <hi>Antinomians</hi> (as they call them) and others about being <hi>juſtified before converſion;</hi> whether a Man be juſtified <hi>before converſion,</hi> or no, or whether he be not ſo afterward, as in ſome Senſe he was not before: I ſay, we are juſtified <hi>in Chriſt</hi> from all Eternity, and we are juſtified <hi>with Chriſt</hi> when we believe.</q>
               </p>
               <p>NOW, if thy <hi>Doctor</hi> be not a thorow pac'd <hi>Criſpian,</hi> I know not who is; and let me tell this <hi>Author</hi> by the way, that if he dare appear openly in this Controverſie, and in which I offer him a full unreſerved meeting, whereunto let him bring what numbers and degrees of Perſons he poſſibly can, either by hook, or by crook, according to the conſtant practiſe of thoſe of his perſwaſion, to back him in the ſame, I queſtion not but by the wiſdom, power, and Grace of God, ſufficiently to manifeſt, that Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi> fully accords with all thoſe more <hi>antient and modern</hi> REFORMERS, truly and undeniably reckoned upon as ſuch (though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps differing in other things,) as to the <hi>Doctrines ef Juſtification, Sanctification, Graces,</hi> and <hi>Duties</hi> thereupon, both in their ſpring, nature, order, form, matter and uſes, and that in the full ſcope, and agreeing with the compleat tenure of the Covenant of <hi>Grace</hi> it ſelf. But our <hi>Author</hi> tells us, <hi>p.</hi> 8. from the text he had cited. <hi>p.</hi> 5. <q>That the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle by way of <hi>Antitheſis,</hi> conſtantly oppoſeth Faith to Works in Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Criſpianiſm <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mask'd,</hi> pag. 8.</note> that is, an act of ours to ſome others of our own, not an Act of ours to one of God, as this <hi>Author</hi> would have us think. The oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, which you may obſerve in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Writings of <hi>Faith</hi> to <hi>Works,</hi> is ſufficient to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51623:9"/> that it is but a Dream of the <hi>Doctor,</hi> that <hi>to be juſtified by Faith,</hi> is to have in our Spirits the Manifeſtation of God's Juſtification. This hath no relation at all to what the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſo often ſaith, <hi>&amp;c, ſo far he.</hi>
                  </q> Now this <hi>Antitheſis,</hi> according to our <hi>Author</hi>'s ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Deſign therein, one Mr. <hi>Antiſozzo</hi> has notably anatomized in his Explication of <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> unto which I refer the <hi>Reader</hi> for his being undeceived, and ſhall let Dr. <hi>Good-win</hi> anſwer this from the fore-mentioned Treatiſe,—</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Whether it be the Act of Faith that juſtifies, or that is accounted a Mans Righteouſneſs, when <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Goodwin <hi>on the</hi> Epheſ. <hi>Part 2d. p.</hi> 301.</note> we are ſaid to be ſaved through Faith? Surely, no, for God might have took work as well, if he would have taken it as an Act, he might have taken any Act, Love it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>THERE is this reaſon lies in the bottom of my Spirit againſt it, beſides all that elſe the Scripture ſaith againſt it; That if when I go to God to be juſtified, I muſt preſent to him my believing, as the matter of my righteouſneſs, and only <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s death as the merit of it (which is the very controverſie on foot this day, for all our <hi>Author</hi>'s ſeeming ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of the righteouſneſs of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the bare inſtrumentality of Faith in the reception thereof in order to our Juſtification) What will follow? Two things are clear to me: Firſt, That the heart is taken off from looking upon the righteouſneſs of <hi>Chriſt</hi> wholly, and diverteth it to it's own righteouſneſs in the very act of believing, for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and preſenteth that to God which the Scripture is clear againſt; I ſay, it doth take the heart off from the righteouſneſs of the <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> or the eying of that, and cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it to divert into it ſelf, and preſent its own Faith to God. Secondly, Every man that will believe to be juſtified, and go to God, and ſay, <hi>Lord juſtifie me,</hi> he muſt have an evidence that he hath Faith, for how elſe can he preſent that as the matter of his righteouſneſs? Now Millions of Souls cannot do this, they were in a poor caſe if they ſhould be put to it.</p>
                  <p>THE Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>it was of Faith that it might be ſure.</hi> If Juſtification had been foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on the act of Faith, it had been as ſure on works as faith; for that faith that draws out an act of love is as apt to fail as that act of love. But here is no uncertainty, while I believe to be juſtified by the righteouſneſs of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> but my faith is ſwallowed up there; though I may doubt of my faith relying on him, yet I have a ſure object; I have a ſure matter to repreſent to God for me, whereas if believing was that I had to repreſent to God to be juſtified by, ſuppoſe my faith fail me, I have not a ſure matter of righteouſneſs to repreſent to God.</p>
                  <p>THE very object Faith believes on is a contradiction to this, that the act of Faith ſhould be the matter of my Juſtification.</p>
                  <p>Yet further—<hi>Q.</hi> Is not faith an act? I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'s true, it is in a <hi>Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical</hi> ſignification an act, but in the ſenſe in the true real import of it, it <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Goodwin <hi>on the</hi> Eph. <hi>part 2d. p.</hi> 287, 288.</note> is <hi>meerly paſſive:</hi> Faith doth not give any thing to God as Charity and Love doth, but it only ſuffers God to be good to it; it takes in that Salvation which grace would beſtow upon it; my Brethren, the hands of all other graces are <hi>working</hi> hands, but the hands of faith are meerly <hi>receiving</hi> hands; now ſaith the Apoſtle. <hi>Not to him that worketh, but believeth:</hi> So that this faith, as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth to Salvation, it is not reckoned a worker, nor doth it look upon it ſelf as ſuch, but a meer receiver, a meer emptineſs, a meer firſt matter and chaos, the form whereof is grace, if I may ſo allude; no grace could have been choſen in the heart of man, ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thus to the grace that giveth, and to the gift it ſelf, as this grace of Faith is.</p>
                  <p>AND there is nothing in Man that anſwers the promiſe; for this grace hath put it ſelf out into promiſes; as the original lies in the heart of God, ſo he hath made out a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py out of himſelf in the promiſes, and nothing anſwers this but faith.</p>
               </q>
               <p>See but the very places that our <hi>Author</hi> quotes out of Dr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> and thou wilt find that this is his plain, yea, literal as well as incluſive Senſe of the whole of that of Faith, as <hi>pag,</hi> 85, 440. 596. compare with our <hi>Author, p.</hi> 8, 9. and be thine own Judge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as to the Wretchedneſs of his Forged Charge againſt him. Further ſays Dr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:51623:9"/> Mark it well Reader, That—</p>
               <q>
                  <p>In Chriſt as a common perſon, and as a pattern of us, we may be ſaid to have done what Jeſus Chriſt did or <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Goodwin <hi>on the</hi> Eph. <hi>part 2d. p.</hi> 216. &amp; —<hi>p.</hi> 145.</note> doth, or what befalleth him; and we are reckoned by God to have done it: My Brethren, this is one of the greateſt hinges of the Goſpel—That way of the <hi>Arminians</hi> doth exceedingly detract from the love of God, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to make him a lover of Mankind; and that that is a thing out of the conſideration whereof he gave his Son, and that he loves them in common, and loves them indefinitely, and if they believe ſo, God will then ſhew love to them. Again, But you will anſwer me, how can this be, that we ſhould be children of Wrath, and yet that God ſhould love us, and out of that Love call us, and yet the Love be the ſame? If they will anſwer me another queſtion, I will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer <note place="margin">
                        <hi>p.</hi> 295, 296, 297.</note> that; and that is this, How was Jeſus Chriſt beloved, and a curſe at the ſame time? Do but anſwer me, how were they in <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. enemies and beloved at the ſame time? Whether did not God actually and really lay the ſins of us all upon Chriſt, who yet at the ſame time was without ſin? And again, Was not Chriſt, when on the Croſs really made ſin? and yet now he is in Heaven, he is without ſin, even in that very reſpect wherein before, when on Earth, he was Sin. Was not Jeſus Chriſt once made ſin in a true real ſenſe? Certainly he was; And is not now Jeſus Chriſt without ſin in the ſame ſenſe? So the Apoſtle ſaith: Now then anſwerably, we may be enemies, and yet loved of God: We may be children of Wrath, and condemned already, in reſpect of that we ſtand in, and afterwards ſaved as truly, as once Jeſus Chriſt was made Sin: <hi>He will appear the ſecond time without ſin,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 28. Is there ſuch an alteration made in Chriſt's condition, and a real one? Certainly there may be the like in ours, in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>ult.</hi> the parallel is exact, <hi>Him did God make to be ſin for us, that knew no ſin, that we might be made the righteouſneſs of God in him.</hi> As on Chriſt's part there was a time when God laid all our ſins upon Chriſt, and then another time, in which he took all our ſins off from him, when he had ſatisfied for them; ſo on ours, there is a time when God doth lay the righteouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt upon us, and takes off that ſtate of wrath that we were in in our own perſons; And as it were abſurd to ſay, (as ſome) that our ſins are tranſlated upon Chriſt then, when we believe; ſo that then we were made the righteouſneſs of God in him, before we are called and believe, in that ſenſe, that the Apoſtle there ſpeaks: The parallel then lies in this, That as there was a time when God laid our ſins on Chriſt, made him ſin, which was on the Croſs, when alſo at the ſame time he was perſonally without ſin; ſo there is a time, when God accounts perſonally to us Chriſt's righteouſneſs. And again, as there ſucceeded a time, when Chriſt that was made ſin, and remained under it for a while, is without ſin (as now for ever he is) ſo there was a time, when we, who are now juſtified, were not juſtified, but were ſinners and children of wrath, and that truly before God, as truly as that now we are ſaved before God. And that is certainly to me the meaning of that in, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 4. <hi>The righteouſneſs of the Law is fulfilled in us.</hi> Do we fulfil the righteouſneſs of the Law? No, but as it was fulfilled in and by Jeſus Chriſt before; ſo the ſame being applied unto us, when we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, is ſaid to be fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>filled in us, <hi>that is,</hi> is made good in us, as we may ſo expreſs it; in that diſcharge of his, we, as conſidered in him, are made the righteouſneſs of God.</p>
                  <p>But you will ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, how are we ſaved in Chriſt, and juſtified in Chriſt, upon believing when we were juſtified from our ſins in Chriſt when he roſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and had ſin taken off from him, did not he repreſent us then?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ADAM</hi>'s inſtance will clear all; were not all Mankind condemned in <hi>Adam?</hi> Yet no man is condemned in his own perſon till he is born, yet repreſentatively in <hi>Adam</hi> all died: ſo it is here, ſo far as we take Chriſt as a common perſon repreſenting us, what was done in him, was done for us in him; and ſo from eternity, before Chriſt died, we were ſaved in him in that ſenſe, <hi>according to the grace which was given in Chriſt before the World began,</hi> ſaith he, in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 9. Chriſt himſelf purchas'd it, with a reſerve till we believe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, or elſe we are not to have the benefit of his death. The Bond lay in God the Father's
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51623:10"/> hand till we ſhould come in to him for it. I do not know that the Scripture uſeth the word <hi>ſaved from everlaſting,</hi> but only that the grace was given us in Chriſt, and that Chriſt died repreſentatively, but when we come to exiſt in our own perſons, then it is applied to us, and we are ſaved in our own perſons by that grace, which once made Jeſus Chriſt <hi>a common perſon</hi> for us.</p>
               </q>
               <p>NOW <hi>our Author</hi> drawing towards a concluſion of this his charge, <hi>p.</hi> 10. brings in his clinching Argumentative Inference, which queſtionleſs he takes to be a very <hi>doughty one:</hi> Namely, <q>That if a Man be juſtified before he believes, then he is not juſtified by faith; that is a plain caſe, ſays he.</q> It is ſo indeed; however, I exceedingly doubt whether in this <hi>our Author,</hi> it be not an amphibious, prevaricating and <hi>Delphian Oracle</hi> Caſe. And to put the matter beyond diſpute, conſider <hi>Reader,</hi> That to be juſtified doth not only import, but irreſiſtibly preſuppoſe an actual, as diſtinguiſhed from a perſonally poſſeſſed intereſt in ſuch a righteouſneſs as that wherein God may, <hi>ſalva juſtitia,</hi> and that not in a remote me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious, but immediate and ſubſtantial ſenſe, without the leaſt interfering with the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, unlimited, ſpotleſs Juſtice and Holineſs of his Divine Nature, whence this Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is reckoned the Righteouſneſs of God, received by Faith; or the compleat and perfect demands of the Law; whence it is alſo, that Chriſt, as being made under the ſame, is accounted in an immediate ſenſe, THE LORD OUR RIGHTEOUSNESS; (the latter being a full revealed Tranſcript of the former) or can groundedly and poſitively in his very act of juſtification, without any manner of reſerves, pronounce us juſt (and that not in a bare meritorious, and as ſuch ſubſervient ſenſe of the ſame, the <hi>Diverting Kettledrum</hi> of theſe our <hi>Spiritual D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>agooners,</hi> to ſtave us off from our diligent attendance upon the <hi>Carb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nado'd</hi> and traduced <hi>Martyrs</hi> and <hi>Witneſſes</hi> of our bleſſed Jeſus, in their diſtinct, as well as materially faithful Teſtimonies concerning him) from and in ſuch a Righteouſneſs, as actually, ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quately, and materially correſponds with the forementioned Perfections of God, both in his Nature and Law; for as poſſeſſion, properly ſuch, gives no man a juridical Title unto that whereinto he enters by poſſeſſion, ſo neither does Faith, which is in this caſe, at moſt a meer poſſeſſing grace, entitle even an elect Veſſel unto any one of the leaſt of the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the whole of Scripture; but it is his juridical forenſick (though founded in grace) relation unto, and intereſt in this Righteouſneſs that gives him an undoubted Title and Right unto his Juſtification, and all that is conſequential of the ſame; hence it is that Faith fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, and that in two reſpects:</p>
               <p n="1">1. AS a manifeſtating or evidencing Inſtrument, with all it's Adjuncts, Concomitants and Subſequents, whence it is, that Chriſt as the Author and Finiſher of the ſame, becomes the Wiſdom of God unto ſuch a Soul.</p>
               <p n="2">2. AS an uniting, applying, clothing, grace-conveying, heart-renewing and fruit-bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inſtrument, and that in all the vigorous exercitious actings thereof, both objectively and ſubjectively; whence it is alſo, that Chriſt as the Author and Finiſher of the ſaid Faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the Power of God unto ſuch a Soul: but all this is meerly the fruit of a previous Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, otherwiſe God could not be juſt in juſtifying, neither could his elect ones be juſtly reckoned upon as Sons, but rather Baſtards or Impoſtors. But all this blunder in <hi>our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,</hi> as in the cloſe of this Charge, <hi>p.</hi> 10, 11. is no more but to bring in the Vertues and Graces of the Spirit, as the matter of our Juſtifying Righteouſneſs, provided that Faith as an Inſtrument, will but eye and betake it ſelf unto the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and engagge the Soul to reſt wholly upon the ſame, in the bare merits thereof, for it's Juſtification be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and Acceptation with the Lord.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Projicit ampullas, &amp; ſeſquipedalia verba.</hi> 
                     <bibl>Hor.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="charge">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:51623:10"/>
               <head>AS to the <hi>Second Charge.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="2">II. HIS <hi>Second Charge, p.</hi> 11. is, That the <hi>Doctor</hi> 
                  <q>Aſſerts and Defends that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin which is the bane of all <hi>godly Fear and Dread,</hi> of all <hi>ſuſpicion of our ſelves, of Spiritual Watchfulneſs,</hi> and <hi>a wary and cautious behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Criſpianiſ. <hi>unmask'd.</hi> p. 11</note> which yet are Graces and Duties much commended in Holy Scripture, and greatly practiſed by the Servants of God.</q> This falſe imputation of his, is managed with the ſame ſcurrilous and lying Spirit, and to the ſame ends that his former and ſubſequent ones, are produced for, againſt <hi>the Dr.</hi> As</p>
               <p n="1">1. THAT he never gives thee an account, upon what grounds it is, that <hi>the Dr.</hi> urges this or the other diſcerpted ſentence, that he, for his own vile ends, does continually through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his <hi>Pamphlet</hi> quote.</p>
               <p n="2">2. NEITHER does he declare for what ends and from what principles (as tending thereunto, together with their uſes and advantages, as aſſigned unto them of the Lord, in their proper places) it is that <hi>the Dr.</hi> ſpeaks for or againſt, both duties and graces. As for inſtance, He tells us, That the <hi>Dr.</hi> 
                  <q>a bold and fearleſs man laughs at ſuch ſilly creatures as <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>diſtruſt</hi> their having Faith or no, and being regenerated and ſanctified or no; and withal that he merrily brings in ſuch an <note place="margin">Criſpianiſ. <hi>unmask'd.</hi> p. 11.</note> one complaining thus, <hi>I have neglected the Day of my Viſitation, I had once the Opportunity, the preſence of the Spirit of God; Alaſs! My fear is, that that was the Day of God's Grace to me, and now there is no more hope left for me.</hi> And thereupon concludes, Which words (as you'll find) he ſpeaks in way of <hi>Mockery:</hi> And in ſeveral other places you will find him deriding ſuch <hi>whining timorous Chriſtians</hi> as theſe, repreſenting them as Perſons of ſhallow Underſtandings, and of a Temper, not becoming the Goſpel.</q> What Ground he hath received for this frontleſs, and wretched Branch of this part of his Charge, let the very place from whence he cites it, determine <hi>p.</hi> 345. where ſpeaking of <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>laying Iniquity upon Chriſt,</hi> that it is ſo entirely his own Act, that none of our Duties, be they the beſt that we can perform, can have any Hand therein. Therefore I ſhall be the more large, in tranſcribing the <hi>Doctor,</hi> even in this Page, and that which follows, that thou mayſt apparently diſcern into the villanous Treachery of this <hi>Author,</hi> and juſtly gueſs thereby at the baſe ends in the ſame. The <hi>Doctor</hi> ſpeaking from thoſe words in <hi>Iſa. chap.</hi> 53. 6. that our Sins are already laid on <hi>Chriſt,</hi> tells us;</p>
               <q>
                  <p>It ſhould therefore ſerve to put the People of God upon the Admiration of the great love of God (ſeeing it is only the Lord that layeth Iniquity upon Chriſt) to give unto the Lord the Praiſe of the Glory of his Grace. Oh! <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Criſp<hi>'s Works.</hi> Vol. II. Pag. 345.</note> let nothing go away with that, ſeeing none but the Lord doth the thing!</p>
                  <p>And to this end, Beloved, the Lord muſt open your Eyes, that you may ſee. It it is he alone that doth it; but till you ſee it, what ever you may think of your ſelves, you will ſanctifie to Nets and Drags inſtead of them. If Righteouſneſs ſeem to be the eaſing of burthens in Spirit, then Righteouſneſs ſhall be, and will be exalted above meaſure. From whence proceeds theſe ſtrange Expreſſions, <hi>Oh the Omnipotency of Faſting and Prayer, and Repentance</hi> I What is this but to give the Glory of the Lord to our ſervices, as if they diſcharge us of our Sins, when it is the Lord only that doth diſcharge us of them? But I muſt haſten.</p>
                  <p>THERE is another obſervable Paſſage in theſe words, more obſervable indeed than heeded by the moſt of them, and that is to be taken from the circumſtance of Time, <hi>when the Lord laid Iniquity upon Chriſt</hi> The Text ſaith, <hi>The Lord hath laid on him the Iniquity of us all. Satan</hi> knows well enough of what great conſequence this Circumſtance of Time is, both to the Manifeſtation of the Glory of God's Grace, and to the eſtabliſhment of the Comforts of God's People, and therefore he hath raiſed a foul Duſt to miſguide poor Wretches, that they may not lay hold upon this Circumſtance, and the Comfort that will
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51623:11"/> flow from it. The Text ſaith not, The Lord <hi>doth</hi> lay Iniquity on him, or the Lord <hi>will</hi> lay Iniquity on him, much leſs that the time is overſlipt now, and the Lord will not lay Iniquity upon him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Satan</hi> is very buſie with tender ignorant Hearts, either to perſwade them that the Work is now a doing, or the Work hereafter ſhall be done, but yet is not done, or the time is overſlipped, it might have been done, if Men had not neglected the Opportunity, but now it is too late, it is never to be done.</p>
                  <p>The laſt of theſe hath troubled the Hearts of many People, whence comes theſe expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: I have neglected the day of my Viſitation, ſaith one, I have neglected the Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, the Preſence of the Spirit of God, my fear is, that was the day of God's Grace to me, but I have let it ſlip, and now there is no more Hope left for me; but Beloved, let the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Word of the Lord himſelf be your guide, and know, that every thing that is ſpoken contrary to the Mind of the Lord, revealed in his Word, is but the natural. Fruit of the Father of Lies, who is a Lyer from the beginning. The Lord <hi>hath laid</hi> Iniquity upon Chriſt: Hath he done it already, and is it now to be done? Nay, hath he done it alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and doth he revoke it, and will not ſuffer it to be done? The point then briefly is this.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THIS Gracious Act of the Lord's laying Iniquity upon Chriſt, is not now, or hereafter to be done, much l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſs a thing he never wills, but it is a thing the Lord hath already done.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>EVERY School-boy will be able to tell you that this Expreſſion <hi>(hath laid)</hi> imports the time paſt, the word being in the <hi>Preter-Perfect</hi> Tenſe; it is not in the <hi>Preſent</hi> Tenſe, nor in the <hi>Future</hi> Tenſe, <hi>the Lord will lay,</hi> but in the <hi>Preter-perfect</hi> Tenſe, <hi>the Lord hath done it,</hi> it is an Act paſt.</p>
               </q>
               <p>NOW, <hi>Reader,</hi> be thy own Judge or deſire no Clandeſtine, or ſurreptatious and forced Subſcriptions from thee; whether Doctrins, Graces and Duties, are not owned by the <hi>Doctor,</hi> provided they be kept within their preſcribed limits, out of, and from which our <hi>Author,</hi> would for a baſe ſelf-juſticiary end divert them, and therefore ſummons us <q>to liſten to what the Infallible Scripture of Truth ſays, <note place="margin">Criſpianiſm <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mask'd.</hi> p. 11, 12, 13, 14.</note> (though for vile and infallible ends, as by him produced) from <hi>Prov.</hi> 28. 14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 12. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4 1. <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m.</hi> 11. 20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 12. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 9.—76. 11.—147. 11. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 5. See <hi>v.</hi> 1, 4. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 28, 29.</q> But ask him, do any of theſe Texts tell us that a Fear and Dread of God, or any other Duty, or Qualification in our Souls, contribute in the leaſt to a laying of Sin upon Chriſt, which ought firſt to have been proved, had he dealt either in a way of reverential awe towards God, or due Reſpect and Regard towards Man? But we ſhall find enough of this as we go on.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="charge">
               <head>As to the Third Charge.</head>
               <p n="3">III. THAT, <q>He hath imbib'd the Principles and Doctrin of this <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Criſpianiſm <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mask'd.</hi> p. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s, (ſays our <hi>Author)</hi> cannot pray.</q> And for this quotes him, <hi>p.</hi> 370. thus,</p>
               <q>
                  <p>When People pray for any Grace (omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting what Intervenes, <hi>viz.</hi> that God hath paſſed over to Men) all their Pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er is, that God would manifeſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not regarding either what goes before, or after; therefore I ſhall tranſcribe the ſubſtance of the ſame. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr. Criſp</hi>'s <hi>Works,</hi> Vol. II. p. 370.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>WELL then, if you pray in Faith, that your Sins are forgiven, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Ground, <hi>(i. e.</hi> our Sins being already laid on Chriſt) becauſe God hath made this Grant, and <hi>you find it upon Record,</hi> then it ſeems your Sins were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given you before your Prayer was made: You will ſay, <hi>God hath granted this before, and now you pray to God that he would make good that Grant to you which he hath granted before.</hi> Beloved, what is thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> more than to make that evident to your Underſtandings, and to give you the knowledge of that which he hath before granted, that you may have the Comfort of it?</p>
               </q>
               <p>I refer the <hi>Reader</hi> to the place it ſelf, for our <hi>Author</hi>'s Refutation, both in the matter, and deſign of his Treacherous <hi>Charges.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:51623:11"/>
               <p> NOW, from whence he runs to his old <hi>Arminian</hi> inference, that <q>If any Man believes this, it is impoſſible he ſhould give himſelf to Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Criſpianiſm <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mask'd,</hi> p. 15.</note> and be frequent and ardent in his Addreſſes to Heaven: For what ſhould he pray for, when there is no obtaining any good at all by it?</q> And thereupon tells us, that to pray for the Forgiveneſs of Sins is needleſs; and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force his malicious Charge, very wretchedly quotes ſeveral Texts of Scripture; as <q>
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.2. — 34.17. — 50.15. — 69.33. — 145.18, 19. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pag.</hi> 16, 17.</note> 
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 15. 29, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. 11, 14. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 10. 12, 13, 14. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. 9. 1 <hi>Kin</hi> 17. 1.—18, 28.—42. 45. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20. 5, 22. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 37. 15, 37. <hi>Jonas</hi> 2. 1. 10. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 8.</q> The <hi>Doctor</hi> ſtill ſpeaking, (which our <hi>Author</hi> never regards in any of his Charges) that our Sins are already laid on Chriſt, therein referring unto a Gracious Act of the Father, as well as compleat undertaking of the Son, and that it is by Prayer we come to receive the full manifeſtative and applicatory Teſtimony of the ſame unto our Souls, and now to put Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yer, Graces of the Spirit, or any other Duty in the room, and place thereof, is not only uſeleſs and unbeneficial, but alſo derogatory unto the Glory of God. Therefore he lays down hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> objections and anſwers in the following words, in the <hi>Page</hi> whence <hi>our Author</hi> cites him—</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Some object and ſay, <hi>Chriſt puts us upon Prayer, and in Prayer that God would</hi> forgive us our Treſpaſſes; <hi>How can our Iniquities <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e laid upon Chriſt already, when we are to pray that God would forgive them to us? It is a vain thing for us to pray to God to forgive them, when they were long ago fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>given.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Criſp's <hi>Work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Vol.</hi> II. p. 369.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwer, They were reckoned to Chriſt long before we pray for the forgiveneſs of our ſins, and yet we do well in the Pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing for the forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of them. We have a common anſwer known to all, There is a twofold forgiveneſs of ſins, a forgiveneſs of ſins in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and forgiveneſs of ſins in the <hi>Conſciences of Men.</hi> Forgiveneſs of ſins in Heaven is that which is acted by God alone: Forgiveneſs of ſins in the Conſciences of Men is the manifeſtation of God's former act. So then to pray for the forgiveneſs of our ſins, is no more but to pray that God would manifeſt to us that God hath forgiven our ſins, and that it may be clear that God hath forgiven our ſins before we do pray for the forgiveneſs of them: And that Prayer is grounded upon God's act before hand made.</p>
                  <p>Conſider this one thing, I would ask this of you, you that pray for forgiveneſs of your ſins, do you pray in Faith, or do you not? If you pray not in Faith, mark what the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that prayeth, let him pray in Faith, nothing doubting; He that wavereth, let him not think he ſhall obtain any thing at the hands of the Lord:</hi> Beloved, your Prayers ſtink and are abominable in the Noſtrils of God if you do not pray in Faith. Well, you pray in Faith you will ſay; if you pray in Faith, if you pray for the forgiveneſs of ſin in Faith, what is the ground of your Faith? If you do believe, you have a ground for your Faith. You will ſay, the Grant and Word of God is <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Page</hi> 370.</note> the ground of your Faith. Well, if the Grant of God be the ground of your believing, then the Grant hath a being before your Faith, and ſo conſequently before your prayer is made.</p>
               </q>
               <p>And do we not know that we ought to pray for the Fall of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and that from this ground, That ſhe is fallen already in the irreverſible determination of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. 8. And though ſhe be not yet actually fallen, muſt we not therefore pray for her fall? Unleſs we can bring God's Decrees and irrevocable Purpoſes actually to depend upon our own Duties and Prayers, This is <hi>our Author</hi>'s conſtant practice, That he would aſſign more to our Duties and Graces (nay, ſo diſpla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e them, that they are neit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er Duties indeed nor Graces, for the obtaining of this or the other benefit and mercy) than unto God himſelf, as the expreſs and fixedly donor of them, even before we ask them, upon which it is indeed, that both our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſting d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſpoſition, receptive and improving ability wholly depends. Hence it is, (under which he betakes himſelf as unto a forlorn refuge, <hi>p.</hi> 16.) That, if ſo, how can we pray for the <hi>hallowing of God's Name,</hi> or that <hi>his Kingdom ſhould come;</hi> whereas, if both of the ſame had not been abſolutely determined of God, the matter of Prayer as enjoyned of Chriſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Diſciples, would have been wholly in vain, ſo the ſame as to the forgiveneſs of ſins or
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51623:12"/> treſpaſſes, he quotes, <hi>p.</hi> 369. out of the Dr's Treatiſe, (which I cannot find, though the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the place has been cited already—) And further proceeds in his quotation from <hi>p.</hi> 561. <hi>That the</hi> Dr. <hi>is an enemy to Prayer,</hi> whoſe citation, and the <hi>Dr</hi>'s end therein I ſhall lay before thee. Thus much he quotes out of him, and annexes it barely unto an act of duty, not regarding wherefore or for what ends the ſame was ſpoken; which take as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows—<q>Beloved Chriſt became our Surety. God accepted of him for our Debt, he cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>'d Chriſt in Goal, as I may ſo ſay, for the debt; God <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Criſp's <hi>Works. Vol.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 560.</note> took every Farthing that he could demand of us; he is now reconciled unto us, he hath acknowledged ſatisfaction, it is upon Record; And now ſhall he come upon them again with freſh wrath, for whom Chriſt hath done all this? Shall he charge the debt upon them again? He hath forgotten the Death of Chriſt it ſeems, if this be true. Therefore know thus much, that it is againſt the Death of Chriſt; it is the making of it of none effect; it makes the coming of Chriſt to be in vain, to ſay that the wrath of God will break out upon <hi>Believers (mark the word)</hi> if they commit ſuch and ſuch ſins. And for this that I have ſaid, <hi>(Now our Proctoring Author comes in)</hi> if any man can produce one Scripture againſt it; if any man can ſhew in all the Book of God, that it is any otherwiſe than I have delivered, for my part, I ſhall be of another mind, and willingly recant my opinion. <hi>But leaves out what follows.)</hi> But I ſee the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture runs wholly in this ſtrain, and is ſo full in no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hing as in this, that God hath gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally diſcharged the ſins of Believers. Oh then take heed of falling into that error of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> that ſay, that God hath taken away the <note place="margin">
                        <hi>p.</hi> 561.</note> ſin, but not the wrath of God due to ſin; that he hath forgiven our ſins, but not the puniſhment of ſin. But I beſeech you conſider, that as our ſins were then upon Chriſt, he was ſo bruiſed for our iniquity, that <hi>by his ſtripes we are healed, and the chaſtiſement of our peace was ſo upon him,</hi> that he being <hi>chaſtiſed for our ſins,</hi> there is nothing elſe but peace belongs to us: And <hi>the chaſtiſement of our ſins was ſo upon him,</hi> that <hi>he beheld the travel of his Soul, and was ſatisfied.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>NOW, <hi>Reader,</hi> thou mayſt ſee who this <hi>Author</hi> is, and what alſo his deſign is, and his falſe repreſentation of the <hi>Doctor,</hi> meerly becauſe he abhors Duties and Graces in a <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>meritorious</hi> ſenſe: This is the plain <hi>Grammar,</hi> as latently radical, of all his virulency againſt him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="charge">
               <head>
                  <hi>As to the</hi> Fourth Charge.</head>
               <p n="4">IV. HE tells us, that—<q>The Doctrin contained in theſe <hi>Sermons,</hi> ſtrikes at all <hi>Godly Sorrow, Contrition, Humiliation, Confeſſion,</hi> and <hi>Lamenting of ſin,</hi> and <hi>Repenting of it,</hi> and renders them uſeleſs and inſignificant in the Life of a Chriſtian.</q> Now what Warrant he hath had for this his bold aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <note place="margin">Criſpi. <hi>unmask'd. p.</hi> 18.</note> a plain, unminced and uncurtailed quotation of <hi>the Dr.</hi> will fully ſatisfie, and alſo diſcover unto thee, and therein, not only <hi>our Author</hi>'s falſe and diſingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous proceedings with <hi>the Dr.</hi> but the ends for which he doth ſo, as alſo the Principles by which he is acted in the ſame. I muſt confeſs unto thee, <hi>Reader,</hi> before we go any further, That unleſs this <hi>Author,</hi> according to the complex account that this his <hi>Treatiſe</hi> gives of him, be a <hi>ROGER<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S L'ESTRANGE REDIVIV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> or as genuine a Spawn dropt from him in one ſenſe or another, as poſſibly can be imagined, I am wholly at a loſs to find him out: And for this obſerve, <hi>p.</hi> 19. where he cites <hi>the Dr. p.</hi> 317, 319, 320. where he never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards in any one of them the diſtinct, yea verbally expreſſed ends of <hi>the Dr.</hi> therein. <q>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe there be a ſin committed, it may be more ſcandalous than ordinary; which ſin perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to ſenſe wounds the Spirit; the Queſtion now is, What it is that muſt or doth aid the Spirit of ſuch an one? of the ſting <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Criſp<hi>'s Works, Vol.</hi> II. <hi>Serm.</hi> 6. <hi>Page</hi> 317, 318.</note> and of the guilt of this or ſuch like tranſgreſſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s committed? What doth diſcharge the ſoul of ſuch a ſin? <hi>(Now our Author <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>mes in,)</hi> Uſually it is taught amongſt us, by thoſe which would be accounted the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51623:12"/> 
                     <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and the greateſt haters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> that the proportion of Repentance, and Tears, and Sorrow, and of Faſting<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oportion of theſe anſwerable to the latitude and height of ſuch tranſgreſſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> eaſe, this takes away the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, this lays the Soul at reſt and quiet it. <hi>(B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>olly di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>regards what follows, namely,)</hi> Therefore when a Soul hath Tranſgr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſed, if i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> moſt or almoſt all the pantings of it are after extraordinary enlargeme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts in bitterneſs and he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vineſs, and mourning, and melting, and tears, theſe are accounte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> they <hi>that waſh away Iniquity.</hi> But beloved, let me tell you, it is impoſſible that all the righteouſneſs of men, though it were more perfect than it can be, ſhould lay one iniquity, or any of the leaſt circumſtance of one iniquity upon Chriſt. If a Man could weep his heart out, if his heart could melt like Wax, and diſſolve into Water, and guſh out River<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs for ſin, all this could not carry away the leaſt dram of the filthineſs of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oul unto Chriſt; nor unload the Soul of any ſin to load Chriſt with it.</q> And is not all this true? can any of our Duties cauſe God to lay ſins upon Chriſt? Doth not herein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the ſecret, yea radical difference (as to what <hi>our Author</hi> would baſely inſinuate both in the matter and manner, and that very di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtortively from what it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t the <hi>Dr.</hi> aſſert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame) between the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> and <hi>Popiſh</hi> Doctrin. See <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8. 13 compard with the <hi>Marginal R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ading,</hi> Where the Lord's charge, even againſt a profeſſing People is not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir rejecti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g of his Sacrifice, but a poſtponi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g of it unto their own, and thereby aſſigning the merit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of all their acceptance both in pardoning and juſtifying Grace unto the Sacrifice of the Lord, provided that their own believing, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have but a precedent, or at leaſt a mixed intereſt therein; but what the conſequence thereof was is evident, even a toral diſappointment of them, not only in their hopes and expectations, but alſo that, That which they ſeemed to have, or thought they had, would prove but an emptineſs or a Lie unto them, in that they ſhould find themſelve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but in <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſtill, <hi>i. e.</hi> neither changed in their ſtate or nature. He further cites him, leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out a part of the Objection, and Anſwer alſo, whence he picks his Charge, wherein thou mayſt yet further ſee into the Orthodoxy of <hi>the Doctor,</hi> together with the <hi>Jeſuitical</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of <hi>our Author.</hi> As—<q>
                     <hi>Obj</hi> But ſome will ſay, <hi>Though our performances do not lay our iniquities upon Chriſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>et they do prevail with God, and</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Criſp<hi>'s Work. Vol.</hi> II. <hi>Serm.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 319.</note> 
                     <hi>move God with pity towards us and ſtir up God to take our iniquites off from us, and lay them upon Chriſt.</hi> (Now <hi>our Author</hi> comes in) <hi>God cannot but melt, will ſome ſay, to ſee the tears of his People, and the bitterneſs of their Spirits, and their crying, and their earneſtneſs, and their ſorrows, Theſe cannot but prevail with him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o have compaſſion on them.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>To which he replies in theſe words, <q>I know this is the general conceit of too many in the World; But beloved, let me tell you, there is nothing in all the Creatures in the World, that hath the leaſt prevalency with the Lord let them do what they can; all our Prayers, all our Tears, all our Faſtings, all our Mournings, all our Reluctancy, and fighting againſt our Corruptions, they move God, not a jot to lay our ſins upon <hi>Chriſt</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But he leaves out what immediately follows, wherein the <hi>Doctor</hi> explains himſelf thus: <q>
                     <hi>God is moved only from himſelf.</hi> If they move God, what muſt they move him to? If God be moved at any thing, he is moved according to the nature of the thing that is done; If the nature of the thing produce evil effects, God muſt be moved to do evil to Men; if good effects, if there be good in the things, they move him to Good: Now I ask, is there good or evil in any thing Men do? When they have ſinned, they pray, and they confeſs, and they mourn, and they faſt, is there evil or good in theſe look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon in their own nature? No Man can deny, but that there is abundance of Iniquity in the beſt Performances a Man doth, and <hi>God is of purer Eyes than to behold Iniquity.</hi> That which muſt move God to do good, muſt have a goodneſs in it ſelf; all the motive therefore in the Lord is ſimply himſelf.</q> Now doth the <hi>Doctor</hi> contradict himſelf at all in any of this? Let him that runs both read and judge. Theſe proceedings in the manner of them, may alluſively be applied unto what old <hi>Jacob</hi> charges upon his Sons, <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi, viz.</hi> That they made him even to ſtink in the Land, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> under a pretence of eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51623:13"/> an <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> which was <hi>Circumciſion;</hi> they had deceitfully and villainouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but gratified their own Luſts by the ſame: Thus it is in reference to Reformation, when Perſons ſo cry up Holineſs (which is an indiſpenſible Qualification, as well as mark of a Child of God) yet ſo as to dethrone what is of a higher nature, both in kind and degree, they are (as experience all along informs us) enforced to betake themſelves to ſuch viſibly-pitiful ſubterfuges, and wretched Prevarications in the Proſecution of their deſigns therein, that even Holineſs and Reformation themſelves, have become nauſeous to them about us; yea, ſuch has been their methods and meaſures in their ſeeming endeavours, after a promoting of them, as that they are ſo far from being truly expreſſive of the ſame, both in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and kind, as that indeed if practically attended unto, would prove deſtructive unto the very receive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dicta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es of the Light of Nature it ſelf, and that in the common moral operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſame: Whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce it is, that true Holineſs in the univerſal nature thereof, is not only ſo little regarded by<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and appearing in moſt of their followers, but alſo become a meer fancy, and but a by-word unto thoſe who expreſly prefer Morality u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to Grace, by deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto them any eſſential difference in the ſame. Theſe things indeed, both in their Principles and Practices, are the very <hi>Achan</hi> of our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and though they have put a ſtop in ſome meaſure unto the Camp of real Reformation in its more apparent progreſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs therein; yet I am ſatisfied that God is in this very day of Controverſie, a leading all ſuch Abbetors of them ſo into the Valley of Deciſion, as will manifeſt that his grand conteſt with them, is not ſo mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h their eſpouſing, but appropriating even of his own truths, his Silver, Gold, and pleaſant things, definitive of the Graces wrought by, and Du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies enabled unto by his own Spirit, unto their own Temples; all which, however black they may ſeem for the preſent, yet are abſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ute Tokens of God's being nigh at ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t with a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed deſign to decide the matter in diſpute; for his ſum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oning of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to, is, (as is evident) but in order to his ſpeedy appearance, <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>el,</hi> 3. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>v.</hi> 1, 14. for God will remember <hi>Amalek,</hi> for ſtanding in the way of <hi>Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ael,</hi> and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a dreadful obliterating remembrance, 1 <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 15. 2, 3. yea, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> how much t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers theſe his <hi>pretended Prophets,</hi> and that with a ſeeming t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry Succeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> acted by a lying Spirit, the ſpeedier, and more total will be both their Diſapp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent and Ruin, 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 22. 19. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is no ſmall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igitating mark of the Hand of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rovidence</hi> in i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſive operation or Wheel, that the Man of Sin ſhould be ſuffered to aſſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to himſelf (notwithſtanding all his ſo long-continued lying, impudent and bloody Villanies) the Title of, <hi>His Holineſs,</hi> and not the <hi>Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d his Righteouſneſs,</hi> in the former of which it is, that not only his <hi>profeſſed,</hi> but alſo <hi>practical</hi> Adherents (who would by no means own him in the bulk or groſs) as in the former, ſo in theſe our days hope in a material Sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied before God, though by a <hi>Salvo,</hi> for fear of the worſt, meritoriouſly for Chriſt's Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs (as the <hi>Quakers</hi> aſſigning unto the Spirit, what indeed is not his undertaken Office) in which it is that, not only his profeſſed, but alſo practical Adherents, as in our day hope in a material ſenſe, to be juſtified before God, though meritoriouſly by the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, according to the ſtated fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mental and more eſtabliſhed <hi>Decrees</hi> and <hi>Canons</hi> of their Counſels, eſpecially th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t of <hi>Trent,</hi> an exact Copy whereof we have flying about our Ears in various <hi>Pamphlets</hi> againſt Dr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> or rather his <hi>Doctrin,</hi> which is the <hi>Scripture-Doctrin of Juſtification.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="charge">
               <head>As to the <hi>Fifth Charge.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="5">V. THOUGH thou wilt find <hi>(Reader)</hi> that as this our <hi>Author,</hi> throughout the whole of his Treatiſe, doth not only (notwithſtanding all his fair pretences) and that under this Head of his Charge, in a more particular manner reject the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, as to its proper and individual matter (wherein it is abſolutely diſtinct from a bare meritorious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd ſubſervient Acceptation of the ſame, <hi>p.</hi> 27. wherein view our <hi>Auth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r)</hi> and Preceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy therein in God's Act of Juſtifying the elect by the Imputation thereof unto their Act of believing, but alſo that there is no eſſential difference between Morality &amp; Grace, as the ſpring of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51623:13"/> this or the other duty, both in the objective and ſubjective operation of the ſame, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the different advantages, ariſing from them; for becauſe that God, as the God of nature, having ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt by <hi>Jonah</hi> Tenders of Mercy unto the <hi>Ninevites,</hi> upon their Repentance, which they cloſing with in the moral diſcharge of the ſame, he thereupon ſpares them. Our <hi>Author,</hi> p. 26. Therefore it is <hi>(I ſay in his Judgment)</hi> that all true Believers in their Addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes unto God for this or the other Mercy in this or the other duty, if they dethrone them, either as proceeding from, or tending to an exaltation of a ſelf-Righteouſneſs to ſelf-end, and therein would cauſe them to neglect the main end, for which they are deſign'd of God, <hi>viz.</hi> the Glory of his great Name, and that in his own way, and by an entire leading them unto a naked Reſting and Dependance upon Chriſt and his Righteouſneſs, for the Accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion both of their Perſons and Performances with God, and alſo their Reception from him, of this or the other Mercy, as their needs require; why then they muſt be termed <hi>Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians;</hi> and when he and his <hi>fraternity</hi> have thus cloathed them with the <hi>Skins</hi> of their own <hi>created Beaſts,</hi> They fall a baiting them with as much virulency, as poſſibly can ſpring from a compleatly grown malice, intermingled with as equal a proportion of Deceitfulneſs and Impudence. This is the very caſe before us, for the clearing of which, let the <hi>Doctor</hi> ſpeak for himſelf, and that from the very places our <hi>Author</hi> fetches againſt him, <hi>p.</hi> 20. He quotes the <hi>Doctor, p.</hi> 140. to ſay, that—<q>A Man gets nothing by all the Righteouſneſs he performs. And he tells us, that he enlarges upon this in his uſual ſcoffing Language, and that with a deſign to caſt away all D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ties.</q> Whereas indeed it is but part of an <hi>Objection,</hi> which the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> lays down and anſwers; that is to ſay, where <hi>ſelf</hi> is brought into the room of, or exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted above the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, all ſuch Actions or Doings will be of no value. As thus,</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj</hi> But ſome may ſay peradventure, <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is is a</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Criſp's <hi>Works,</hi> Vol, I. Ser. 9. Pag. 140.</note> 
                     <hi>way to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>verthrow all Righteouſneſs at one clap. What! all that ever a Man doth, though he doth it never ſo ſpiritually, though never ſo ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ctly, to no purp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſe, and in vain! D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th a Man get nothing by all the Righteouſneſs he performs?</hi> (Here our <hi>Author</hi> comes in, and leaves out what follows) <hi>Then we had as good ſit ſtill, and do nothing at all,</hi> will ſome ſay.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is carnal reaſoning indeed; look but into the ground of this Argument and it will diſcover nothing but the ſelfiſhneſs of the perſon that makes it. I dare be bold to ſay, that that perſon that will do no righteouſneſs, but ſimply for his own ſake; who if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſhould know beforehand, that this <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> will get him nothing, will therefore fit ſtill and do nothing; I dare be bold to ſay, he had as good ſit ſtill indeed, and do nothing: He ſerves himſelf, not God; and though he doth perform righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ever ſo exactly, if he ſerves himſelf, God will never reckon that he ſerves him. When <hi>Self</hi> is eyed, we can never ſerve <hi>God;</hi> when, if our Commodity and Advan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>age be not in the thing, we will ſit ſtill. And is not this a truth? But yet further <hi>our Author p.</hi> 21. he quotes <hi>the Dr. p.</hi> 136. To faſt ſin out, to pray it out, to mourn it out, this is that which muſt bring you tidings; <hi>but leaves out,</hi> This is that which muſt bring you a diſcharge of your ſins <hi>And ſo go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s on in his Charge</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Criſp<hi>'s Works, Vol.</hi> 1. <hi>Serm.</hi> 9. <hi>p.</hi> 136.</note> 
                     <hi>without regarding what fol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ows, viz.</hi> Beloved, let me deal plainly and freely with you, They that do put deliverance from Sin and Wrath upon the ſpiritual performances of that <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> which the Law doth command of them, they do put that <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> in the room and place of <hi>the Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> they do make it as great an Idol as can be, for they do make that Righteouſneſs to be that, which <hi>God's Righteouſneſs</hi> only is. I ſpeak not againſt the doing of any Righteouſneſs according to the will of God revealed: Let that Mouth be for ever ſtopped, that ſhall be opened to blame the Law that is holy, juſt and good, or ſhall be a means to diſcourage People from walking in the Commandments of God blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs.</p>
               </q>
               <p>Now who is the greater <hi>Scoffer</hi> at Religion, or the things of God? he that prefers the righteouſneſs of Chriſt unto his own righteouſneſs, may ſafely determine between this <hi>our Author</hi> and the <hi>Doctor.</hi> But he tells us, <hi>ibid.</hi> from the <hi>Dr. p.</hi> 235. <q>That if a Soul <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51623:14"/> under a full Sail, fill'd with a ſtiff Gale of the Spirit, <hi>&amp;c,</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>That the</hi> Dr. <hi>therein ſpeaks rudely and prophanely, as deriding the aſſiſtance of the Holy Spirit.</hi> But he leaves out his end therein as follows, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>But under favour, the attribut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Criſp's <hi>Works, Vol.</hi> II. <hi>Serm.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 235, 236.</note> of ſuch efficacy to this Righteouſneſs, though thus aſſiſted by Chriſt's Spirit, is more than is meet, though Chriſt be explicitely owned as the Author of ſuch aſſiſtance; the righteouſneſs ſo aſſiſted hath no efficacy at all to obtainany thing of the Lord, but rather an efficacy to haſten and multiply wrath, in that it multiplies ſin.</p>
                  <p>THE righteouſneſs with which we come to God, though we bring with it the Water of the Spirit of Chriſt, to waſh away our old dung, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>p.</hi> 236.</note> yet there is ſuch filth in the Veſſel of our preſent righteous actions, that the action doth but add dung to dung, inſtead of waſhing dung away. Again, <hi>our Author, p.</hi> 22. quotes <hi>the Dr p.</hi> 150. The ſum of which (he tells us) is, That neither Prayer, nor Hamiliation, nor Repentance, nor any other Duties whatſoever, though they be done moſt ſincerely, ſervently and zealouſly, though the perſons that do them <hi>be helped by the Holy Spi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>it therein,</hi> are means of procuring <note place="margin">Criſpian <hi>unmask'd p.</hi> 22.</note> any Bleſſing from God. They never prevent any Evil or Danger, they cannot divert God's Wrath and Diſpleaſure, they conduce not one jot to our peace and joy of Mind, to our comfortable Walking; they afford us no hopes of the Forgiveneſs of Sin, and the Favour and Love of God, and (as you ſhall he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards) they cannot be made uſe of as Signs and Tokens of the goodneſs of our condition. Now hear what <hi>the Dr.</hi> ſays—The Scripture is marvelous plentiful in this, that no Believer for whom Chriſt died, ſhould have the leaſt <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Criſp'<hi>s Works, Vol.</hi> I. <hi>Serm.</hi> 10. <hi>p.</hi> 150.</note> thought in his heart of promoting or advancing himſelf, or any end of his own, by doing what he doth. And though as People may think, here is a marvellous diſcouragement to Perſons, to do what God calls them to do, when they ſhall have nothing for it: I anſwer, when there is a ſpirit of ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity (as you know there is even in the World) they ſhall be as induſtrious to glorifie God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and do good to Men, as if they did it for themſelves. They ſhall do as much for good already beſtowed, as if they were to procure it by their own doing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> I anſwer, there can be no diſcouragement at all unto the performance of any thing God calls for at your hands, though you get nothing in the World by what you d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, I ſay, there is no diſcouragement, becauſe you cannot propound or intend to your ſelves any poſſible gain by Duty; But that, whatever it is, that is a Spur and Encouragement unto Duty, is already freely and graciouſly provided for you to your hand; that all your indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry could not compaſs and bring in, either ſo certainly, or ſo plentifully as the very grace of God, before the performance of any Duty hath provided and eſtabliſhed that good for you.</p>
               </q>
               <p>In the cloſe of this <hi>Charge, p.</hi> 28, 29. <hi>Our Author</hi> unravels (like the old Journey-Man-Taylor) the whole of his twiſted and forced <hi>Sarcaſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> againſt <hi>the Dr.)</hi> though under this pretence, as if he contradicted himſelf, whereas indeed it is no more than his aſſigning unto Graces and Daties their proper places, both as to the ſpring, exerciſe, uſes and ends of the ſame, which <hi>our Author</hi> hath as great a regard unto as the <hi>Turk</hi> himſelf, whence it evidently appears, That <hi>our Author</hi>'s zeal in this cauſe, is but the very ſelf-ſame, both as to the matter and end thereof, as that of the <hi>Jews</hi> mentioned by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 9. 31, 32. <hi>chap.</hi> 10. 2, 3, 4.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="charge">
               <head>From hence he flies to his <hi>Sixth Charge.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="6">VI. That the <hi>Author</hi> ſhould deny, <hi>That we ought to make any uſe of our Graces as Marks, Tokens, or Evidences of our State of Salvation. Author. p.</hi> 29. This falſhood will ſoon be detected from the very places whence he partially cites the ſeeming matter of his miſerable invective a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; for with our <hi>Author,</hi> unleſs the Graces of the Spirit be allowed as the very mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of our Righteouſneſs, and that in, though not for which (that being transferred over
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51623:14"/> to the merits of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, as abſtracted from the real, actual or ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Matter of the ſame) we muſt be juſtified before God, <hi>Antinomianiſm</hi> is preſently ſet on foot, as will appear from the way of his procedure, in his quoting the <hi>Doctor, pag.</hi> 106, 432, 446, 462. Vol. 3. Serm. 3. 447, 453, 465, 469.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Doctor,</hi> in the whole of what our <hi>Author</hi> quotes of him, declares, that what-ever Marks or Signs we may have of Grace, yet if they proceed not from our actual Intereſt in Chriſt and his Righteouſneſs, they will prove but deceitful, there being that in Morality (which as the common Herb in the Field, hath a very nigh reſemblance unto that in the Garden) that be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs a cloſe comparate likeneſs with that of Grace. Unto which places, <hi>ut priùs,</hi> that he quotes of the <hi>Doctor,</hi> I refer the <hi>Reader</hi> for his ſolution. Only to avoid a further Tediouſneſs, I ſhall recite one paſſage of the <hi>Doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs</hi> in reference to this Charge, whereunto many ſcores might be added. And that from <hi>p.</hi> 457. ſpeaking from <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 2, 3, 4: ſays he, <q>Obſerve it well, here is a Zeal, that is, an earneſtneſs of Spirit, and this Zeal was after God, ſo then it was a Zeal, wherein they ſought God and his Glory, not in an indirect way neither, nor in a corrupt way <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Criſp'<hi>s Works,</hi> Vol. II. Ser. 13. Pag. 457.</note> of their own deviſing; but it was a Zeal exerciſed in the Righteouſneſs according to the Law of God himſelf, for ſo much i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> intimated when it is ſaid, that Chriſt is the end of the Law: And yet for all this, ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> though they had this <hi>Zeal of God</hi> according to the Will of God in his Law; yet notwithſtanding, they <hi>ſubmitted not themſelves to the Righteouſneſs of God.</hi> So then there may be a ſingleneſs of Heart to the Lord, and for the Glory of God, and a walking in Obedience to the Will of God revealed in his Law; yet notwithſtanding there may be no portion in Chriſt, but a withſtanding of Chriſt, and not a ſubmitting to his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</q> Thus he deals with the <hi>Doctor</hi> all along; that when and where-ever he finds him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grading or depreſſing of Graces and Duties from an Uſurpation or unſciptural Aſſent, he ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atches out, to preſent before us the bare Expreſſions themſelves, without a candid Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unto us of the <hi>Doctors</hi> Deſign therein, as to the reference they have to the genuine Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his Diſcourſe thereupon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="charge">
               <head>As to the <hi>Seventh Charge.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="7">VII. He tells us, that <q>Another poſition of this our <hi>Author, (i. e.</hi> the <hi>Doctor)</hi> is, <hi>That God is not angry with any elect Perſon, before or after he is converted. If we tell Believers,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>That except they perform ſuch and ſuch Duties,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Criſpi. Unmask'd, <hi>Pag.</hi> 35.</note> 
                     <hi>except they walk thus and thus Holily, and do theſe and theſe Works, they ſhall come under Wrath, at leaſt God will be angry with them, what do we in this but abuſe the Scriptures?</hi>
                  </q> Theſe are his very words, ſaith our <hi>Author,</hi> from <hi>p.</hi> 559. ſo they are indeed; but not wholly his words, nor ſenſe, which are as follows: <q>
                     <hi>If they ſhould ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie them, and make them to believe, being Believers; for of thoſe I ſpeak, if they commit theſe and theſe Sins, they ſhall be damned, and ſo come under the wrath of God.</hi>
                  </q> Then comes our <hi>Author</hi> in with his Charge before-cited, leaving out alſo what follows, as that <hi>we undo all that Chriſt hath done; we injure and wrong the Believers themſelves, we tell that God he lies to his Face;</hi> for if we tell Believers, that except they do theſe and theſe good Works, they ſhall come under the Wrath of God, what is this but to tell God he lies, and to bring the Faithful under a Covenant of Works? Look into the 54th of <hi>Iſaiah, ver.</hi> the 9th, and you ſhall ſee how it is a belying of God, to ſay, that Believers may come under Wrath and Damnation, except they do thus and thus. Further he quotes the <hi>Doctor,</hi> p. 363, 364. very partially, omitting what introduces the ſame; namely, that ſome conclude, that <q>Elect Perſons are in a damnable eſtate, in the time they walk in exceſs of Riot, before they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</q> Where the <hi>Doctor,</hi> ſpeaking of the nature of <hi>Election,</hi> he wholly omits his purpoſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and therefore alſo he leaves out what immediately follows, which he knew would have overthrown his deſign, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <q>It is true, ſuch an Elect Perſon, not called, is never able
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51623:15"/> to know individually of himſelf, that he is ſuch an one that God hath nothing to charge upon him, becauſe, till calling, God gives not unto Perſons to believe; and it is only believing that is evidence to <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Criſp'<hi>s Works,</hi> Vol. II. Serm. 9. Pag. 364.</note> Men of things not ſeen. Things that are not ſeen, are hidden and ſecret, and ſhall not be known: I mean, the things of God's Love to Men ſhall not be known to particular Men, till they do believe; but conſidering their real condition, the Lord hath not one ſin to charge upon an elect Perſon; from the firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of conception, till the laſt minute of his Life, there is not ſo much as Original Sin to be laid on him; and the Ground is, The <hi>Lord</hi> hath laid it on Chriſt already: He did lay Sins on him. <hi>When</hi> did he lay them on him? When did he pay the firſt price of them? Now, ſuppoſe this Perſon uncall'd commits Iniquity, and that this Iniquity is charged upon him; ſeeing that his Iniquities are laid upon Chriſt already, how comes it to paſs that they are charged upon this elect Perſon again? How come they to be tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from Chriſt again, and laid upon this Perſon? Once they were laid upon Chriſt, it muſt be confeſſed. <hi>For the Blood of Chriſt cleanſeth us from all ſins,</hi> 1 Joh. 1. 7. ſaith the Apoſtle; and <hi>by one Sacrifice he hath perfected for ever them that are Sanctified,</hi> Heb. 10. 14. Was there by one Act of Chriſt the expi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tion of Sin, and all at once, that are commited from the beginning of the World to the end thereof, how comes it to paſs, that this and that Sin ſhould be charged upon the Elect Perſons, when they were laid upon Chriſt long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? He did by that one Act of his expiate all our Sins, or did not: If he did not expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate them fully, then he did not <hi>ſave to the utmoſt all them that come to God by him.</hi> But if he did, then all Iniquity is vaniſhed and gone, he did extract it out, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ſome Plaiſter of excellent Virtue, doth extract out the Venom of a plague-ſore: So Chriſt, by once of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering up himſelf, did take away and evaporate all the Sins of the Elect at once.</q> Again our <hi>Author,</hi> to level his ſecret <hi>Armisian</hi> ſtroke againſt <hi>Election</hi> here, as formerly againſt the <hi>Doctrin of Juſtification</hi> in the <hi>materi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Righteouſneſs</hi> thereof, he defiles and pollutes (if poſſible) even Scripture it ſelf, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a bold <hi>Impoſtor,</hi> for it to ſpeak for him, and againſt its Divine <hi>Author;</hi> and in order <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> he cites <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 13. chap. 1. 1. chap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2 3. John 3. 36. and from hence concludes,<q>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>efore they were converted they were <hi>Strangers</hi> and <hi>Aliens,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Criſpi. <hi>unmask'd,</hi> Pag. 36.</note> they were <hi>with at Chriſt, without God, without Hope,</hi> they were at En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity with the Father and the Son, and there was no more to be laid to their charge at that time, than to the glorified Saints above? When they were <hi>without Chriſt,</hi> in the time of their Unregeneracy, and living in all Exceſs of Riot, were they not only in God's Favour, but as much as the Saints in Glory? How then was <hi>Chriſt their Peace?</hi> How is it ſaid they were <hi>reconciled? v.</hi> 16. <hi>Reconciliation</hi> ſuppoſes falling out, it implies being at enmity. Thoſe who are now reconciled, and made Friends, were once <hi>Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> and Enemies; and were they at that very time Favourites of God, yea, as great Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites as the bleſſed glorified Spirits? Who hath the Confidence to ſay this but Dr. <hi>Criſp?</hi> And who hath a Heart to believe it but one that diſ-believes the plain Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Holy Scripture?</q> Hence obſerve, <hi>Reader,</hi> the <hi>Doctor,</hi> having ſpoken of <hi>Election</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and therein in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>luſively notes, That as ſuch, it is a Doctrinal Truth, wherein the irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragable ſafety, and unerring ſecurity of all ſuch comprehended therein, doth radically lie, and this ariſing from a diſtinguiſhing love in God, whence a further free act of his Grace towards them did ſpring and that in ſending his only begotten Son into the World as their repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Head, charged with their Sin to remove the ſame, upon the performance of which (infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the word upon the Croſs, <hi>It is finiſhed)</hi> a door, paſſage or entrance was made or laid open (without the leaſt impeachment of any of the <hi>Attributes</hi> of God) for the actual conveying, in a way of <hi>Application</hi> by faith, that <hi>Reconciliation, Life</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> that God had in ſtore for them from all Eternity, therefore ſaid to be in Chriſt, reconciling them unto himſelf, even before they become by faith reconciled unto him, for it is not Faith that gives a being unto this <hi>Reconciliation in God,</hi> no nor yet the Blood of Chriſt himſelf, though it make way to the uttermoſt for the communication of the ſame, without which
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51623:15"/> it would have been for ever hid even from the <hi>Elect,</hi> but receives it, which the Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly declares to be the very Miniſtry given unto him and others, and adds hereunto the reaſon thereof (the ſo much deſpiſed fundamental truth this day) by way of encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to bring poor ſinners in (Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi>'s own method) <hi>for he hath made him to be ſin for us, who knew no ſin, that we might be made the Righteouſneſs of God in him,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 18, 19, 20, 21. Now doth it follow, that becauſe the <hi>Elect,</hi> during their ſtate of total unbelief, are <hi>Aliens</hi> and <hi>Strangers</hi> unto theſe great Myſteries, that therefore God ſhould not know them as being in Chriſt, as a publick Perſon, and as ſuch, through him be reconciled unto them? 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 19. Or have any of the <hi>Elect</hi> any more by Faith in their actual poſſeſſion, than what they had through Grace an irreverſible Title unto <hi>from all Eter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ity? Tit.</hi> 1. 1, 2. But <hi>our Author</hi> tells us (of which he ſeems to be very fond by his bandying of it backwards and forwards againſt the <hi>Dr.)</hi> That, <hi>Becauſe, whilſt even the Elect are in a ſtate of Nature, they are the Children of Wrath, and alſo, that they that believe not, the wrath of God abideth on them, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they cannot be as much the Favourites of Heaven, as the Saints now in Glory are.</hi> I beſeech thee, <hi>Reader,</hi> mark it well, and a very ordinary capacity will introduce thee not only into the fallacy of his proceedings, but the <hi>Arminian</hi> rottenneſs of his <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>king under the ſame. From whence is it that they come to be tranſlated out of a ſtate of Nature into that of Grace? or to be actually removed from an obnoxiouſneſs unto, and an eternal abid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under the Wrath ſpoken of? (which indeed is the portion of <hi>Reprobates,</hi> amongſt which <hi>Hypocrites</hi> and <hi>Double-Dealers,</hi> eſpecially if <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> and thoſe of them with a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs indeed, who would, under a pretence of Holineſs, carry on their ſiniſter ends by thoſe ways and means which are abſolutely inconſiſtent with the ſame) I ſay, is it from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or from God? If the former, then we are not deceived in theſe <hi>our Adverſaries,</hi> but know where they are; if they ſay the latter, then it is evident that their own <hi>Conceſſions</hi> muſt give their <hi>Aſſertions</hi> the Lie; for it is either in the ability of the <hi>Elect</hi> to diſcern into, and alſo change both the ſtate of their Perſons, and frame of their Natures; or, it wholly lies in God, and that both as to his Will and Power therein: But in <hi>our Author</hi>'s ſenſe, there is nothing but wrath in God againſt them all whilſt in unbelief; what then in God muſt be the motive to remove this unbelief, for a juſtly provoked wrath, in my apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, would ſcarcely be moved to ſtep one ſtep to work that in man which muſt remove and annihilate it ſelf, and indeed it were unreaſonable to expect it. Therefore certainly it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to me, That this <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief,</hi> which in it ſelf expoſes to the wrath of God, muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved by its contrary, which is <hi>Faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and this is wrought by the mighty operation of God. Now whether this proceeds from Love, even the very ſame the Saints in Glory are undiſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedly filled with, and conſequently <hi>Reconciliation</hi> in all the fruits of the ſame, the former be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the root-cauſe of the latter, let the <hi>Learned Athenian Club</hi> determine, in the next of their moſt admirably <hi>unintelligible Debates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obſerve <hi>Reader,</hi> that Scripture, Exod. 34. 6, 7. <hi>And the Lord paſſed by before him, and proclaimed, The Lord, the Lord God, merciful and gracious, longſuffering, and abundant in goodneſs and truth. Keeping mercy for thouſands, forgiving iniquity, and tranſgreſſion, and ſin, and that will by no means clear the guilty, viſiting the iniquity of the Fathers upon the Children, and upon the Childrens Children, unto the third and to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ourth Generation.</hi> Where the Lord proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Name to be, <hi>The Lord God merciful and gracious, long-ſuffering &amp;c.</hi> yet declares, <hi>That he will by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o means clear the guilty:</hi> Now one would think according to our <hi>Neonomian Scheme,</hi> That this is highly incongruous; for who can be more properly the object of this grace than the guilty? And yet the Lord will not pardon theſe, though he pronounces himſelf to be <hi>a God forgiving iniquity, tranſgreſſion and ſin;</hi> who then will he pardon? Why the Text infers, thoſe that are clear from guilt; but where ſhall he find them? ſince the moſt holy that ever was or ſhall be on Earth, never yet was <hi>without ſin;</hi> nay, <hi>he charges even his Angels with folly.</hi> It is only his <hi>Elect</hi> and <hi>Redeemed</hi> ones that he will pardon, and that becauſe he hath provided for them ſuch a righteouſneſs and price to cover their naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and pay off their ſcores, That though they be guilty in themſelves, and that as conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in their natural ſtate, and <hi>Covenant-relation</hi> unto <hi>Adam,</hi> together with the corrupt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filements of their Natures thereupon, and ſo lies obnoxious unto Divine Wrath and Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, yet he, freely of his grace, juſtifies, pardons and acquits them, as being in Chriſt,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51623:16"/> though ungodly in themſelves, and thereupon effectually renews and ſanctifies them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 24, 25, 26. <hi>chap.</hi> 4. 5. <hi>John</hi> 17. 6. compar'd with <hi>v.</hi> 17. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. 8, 9. <hi>Mal.</hi> 4. 2. And hence it is, that he <hi>ſees no ſpot in his Spouſe, nor iniquity in</hi> Jacob. Hence it is alſo, that the Lord before he makes thus known himſelf unto <hi>Moſes</hi> in this his <hi>gracious,</hi> and yet <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious Proclamation,</hi> doth not only change his covenant ſtation, by putting him upon a rock, but alſo covers him with a compleat, unſpotted, and yet external Righteouſneſs, by <hi>his</hi> putting of him into a Clift of the ſaid Rock, as not willing that Chriſt, who indeed was figured out by that Rock, ſhould become a pedeſtal for <hi>Moſes,</hi> to ſtand upon before God in his own inherent righteouſneſs of Faith, Repentance and Sincerity, but he muſt be clothed with, or put on Chriſt, in <hi>his</hi> own Righteouſneſs, even his actual obedience unto the precep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and ſanction-part of the Law, and that in the ſolid matter, and not meritorious or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequential effects of the ſame, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 9.</p>
               <p>Let me further tell thee, <hi>Reader,</hi> and by then thou haſt thoroughly ſearch'd into the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonancy of <hi>Scripture,</hi> thou wilt certainly find it ſo, That as on the one hand no one's holineſs, though of the right kind, can or ever did produce the leaſt dram or particle of the <hi>Love of God,</hi> ſo neither will i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the perfection of it's degree, in Glory it ſelf, when without all ſpot or blemiſh, prove or appear to be the matter wherein their juſtified eſtate doth conſiſt. Nay, take the very merits of Chriſt themſelves, properly and diſtinctly as ſuch, and they will not ſubſerve ſo unſcriptur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l an end, for though the <hi>King's Daughter be all glorious within,</hi> in the real and true renovation of her Nature here, whilſt upon Earth, and unſpotted perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction thereof in Glory, yet that which gives her admittance into, and an eternal ſtanding before God, is her clothing or covering, nor the former, which is indeed but a reſult of the latter, and that not in a remote <hi>meritorious</hi> ſenſe, but material and ſubſtantial intereſting of her in, and inveſting of her with that <hi>Gold of</hi> Ophir, or Garment wrought <hi>of Gold,</hi> which is the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs <hi>of the Saints, Pſa.</hi> 45. 9, 13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 8.</p>
               <p>THIS appears from the nature and manner of Chriſt's proceedings on his juridical Throne at the day of Judgment, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. 31, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (A Text out <hi>Adverſaries</hi> ſo imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently urge to prove that inhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent righteouſneſs is the matter in which, though for the merits of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, all that ſhall be ſaved, are juſtified, or prono<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nced <hi>juridically juſt before God)</hi> wherein it is evident, That the whole of the eternal Counſels of God, concerning Mankind in the Judgment committed by the Father unto the Son are demonſtratively ſet forth in the very form of Chriſt's proceedings on that day, and that to the ſtopping of the Mouths of <hi>Angels, Men</hi> and <hi>Devils,</hi> together with the Manifeſtations of the faithfulneſs of Chriſt in the diſcharge of his <hi>Mediatory Office,</hi> by bringing about the full and undeniable accompliſhment of the aforeſaid Counſels, not only in the very matter, but order, and regular courſe, and manner of the ſame. In ſhort, the whole of the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions of that day will appear to be (as ſententially declar'd by Chriſt) a perfect Epito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mized Tranſcript of the ſecret of God's Covenant, As</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Doctrin of Election,</hi> wherein God's eternal purpoſe of Love towards a certain number of the Lump or Maſs of Mankind, without any regard unto, by way of motive or foreſight of their believing or juſtified ſtate, fully appears, therefore called <hi>Sheep (ſeparate the Sheep from the Goats)</hi> even before they were ſo much as actually changed in their ſtate, <hi>v.</hi> 32. comp. <hi>John</hi> 10. 16.</p>
               <p n="2">2. THE <hi>Doctrine of Juſtification,</hi> is made manifeſt in <hi>Chriſt's ſetting</hi> them <hi>on his right hand,</hi> or changing their ſtation, which precedes his owning any of their works, <hi>v.</hi> 33. comp. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 5.</p>
               <p n="3">3. THE <hi>Doctrin of Regeneration,</hi> atteſted unto in the fruits of the ſame, even good works from a gracious principle to a right end, and their ſelf denial thereupon, <hi>v.</hi> 35, 36, 37, 38, 39, 40. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. 13. <hi>Their works follow,</hi> but go not before <hi>them,</hi> compare <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 22. <hi>Luke</hi> 13. 26.</p>
               <p n="4">4. ALL this is apparently founded upon their being bleſſed of the Father; but when was that? Even then when he had prepared a Kingdom for them, and that <hi>from the Foundation of the World, v.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4. comp. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 9. whereupon it is, that the bleſſed Son reſigns up <hi>his Mediatory Office</hi> and Kingdom unto the Father, together with the truſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 24. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 13. whereby <hi>God becomes All in All.</hi> Where
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51623:16"/> now is <hi>room</hi> for boaſting, ye pitiful Huckſters in <hi>Divinity?</hi> Where are you <hi>cauſa ſine qua nons,</hi> your <hi>Conditions, Cauſes</hi> and <hi>Prerequiſites?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>BUT we muſt attend <hi>our Author,</hi> who quotes <hi>the Dr. p</hi> 15. <q>Though a Believer, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he be a Believer, doth ſin often, yet God no longer ſtands offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and diſpleaſed with him, when he hath once received Chriſt.</q> And <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Criſp's <hi>Works, Vol.</hi> I. <hi>Serm.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 15.—<hi>Quoted by</hi> Criſpia. <hi>unmask'd. page</hi> 37.</note> hench he gives what he thinks to be <hi>the Dr</hi>'s reaſon, on which our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deller fixes his miſtake, but perfectly leaves out the bottom-ground there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, by which <hi>our Author</hi> gives us ſome <hi>Socinian</hi> glimmerings, more of which both as to the matter and clearneſs, we may ſee in his next <hi>Charge,</hi> for <hi>ibid.</hi> here he tells us,<q>His reaſon is, becauſe if Chriſt bore our Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, he alſo bore the diſpleaſure of God for them; and though God be diſpleaſed at ſin in Believers, and hates and abhors it, yet he is not offended with the Perſons of Believers, who commit that ſin, becauſe they are juſtified.</q> Now compare this with what he leaves out in the ſame <hi>Page,</hi> unquoted from <hi>the Dr.</hi> as follows, whence thou mayſt have a little view of <hi>Socinus</hi>'s Face, though pictut'd or ſhadow'd forth in what <hi>our Author</hi> ſays, but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſide-ways—<q>And (ſaith the <hi>Dr.)</hi> unto them, God ſaith, <hi>Anger is not in me, Iſa.</hi> 27. 4. And <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. amongſt many other notable expreſſions of God's being well pleaſed towards poor Sinners through Chriſt: He ſaith, he <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Criſp's <hi>Works, Vol.</hi> I. <hi>Serm.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 15</note> was wounded for their tranſgreſſions; you have this admirable expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the effect of his wounding, <hi>He ſhall ſee the Travel of his Soul,</hi> that is, towards the latter end of the <hi>Chapter, And he ſhall be ſatisfied; ſatisfied</hi> here, is as much as <hi>pacified,</hi> they are all one; The Travel of the Soul of Chriſt makes God ſuch amends for the ſinfulneſs of all Believers, that he can no longer ſtand offended and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with them. If God doth remain offended with them, there is yet ſome of their ſinfulneſs remaining to be taken away, that this offence alſo may be taken away. All their ſins muſt be taken away from them, and all offences will be removed from them. But except God will be offended, where there is no cauſe to be offended, (which is Bla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy to ſpeak) he will not be offended with Believers. For I ſay he hath no cauſe to be offended with a Believer, becauſe he doth not find the ſin of the Believer to be the Believer's own ſin, but he finds it the ſin of Chriſt: <hi>He was made ſin for us, God laid the Iniquity of us all upon him: The Blood of Chriſt cleanſeth us from all Sin: He bore our ſins in his body on the Tree.</hi> And if he bear our ſins, he muſt bear the diſpleaſure for them; nay, if he did bear the diſpleaſure, the indignation of the Lord; and if he did bear the indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lord, either he did bear all, or but part; if he did not bear all the indignation of the Lord, then he doth not <hi>ſave to the uttermoſt thoſe that come to God by him,</hi> as in the ſeventh <hi>Chapter</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> he is ſaid to do; I ſay, not to the uttermoſt becauſe hee is ſome offence, ſome indignation left behind, and for lack of taking of this indignation upon himſelf, it lights and falls upon Believers. So that, either you muſt ſay, Chriſt is an imperfect Saviour, and hath left ſome ſcattering of wrath behind, that will light upon the head of the Believer; or elſe you will ſay, he is a perfect Saviour, and takes away all diſpleaſure of God; then there remains none of it upon the Perſon of the Believer. Beloved, for my part, I underſtand not what clouds are in the Mind and Judgment of other men: To me it ſeems, there is no truth more abundantly cleared in all the Scripture, than this one truth of the tranſacting of our ſins, and conſequently the offence or God for this Sin, that it is wholly laid upon the back of Chriſt, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Criſp's <hi>Works Vol</hi> I. <hi>Ser.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 16</note> and ſo a poor ſoul hath reſt from the indignation of God, as Chriſt doth take the burthen off from his ſhoulders. There is a two-fold burthen; firſt in ſin it ſelf, and the ſecond burthen is the indignation of God for it. Who can bear this indignation of his? Chriſt alone, and he hath born it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>NOW from hence thou mayſt obſerve no ſmall little of <hi>our Author</hi>'s Treachery, and what <hi>Arminianiſm,</hi> as well as <hi>Socinianiſm</hi> lodges in the ſame, notwithſtanding his ſeemingly fair acknowledgments of <hi>commutative imputation of Sin and Righte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſneſs between Chriſt and a Believer. The Dr.</hi> as we have heard, poſitively as well as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrantably declares, That God cannot be diſpleaſed with the perſon of a believing Sinner in a proper, vindicative or legally penal ſenſe, becauſe that his ſins were laid upon Chriſt, and that he alſo bore actually, in the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51623:17"/> room of ſuch, even God's diſpleaſure againſt the ſame. Therefore, ſays <hi>our Author, ut ſupra</hi> That becauſe Chriſt bore our iniquities, he <hi>alſo</hi> bore the diſpleaſure of God for them, which he takes to be a miſtaken ground for the <hi>Dr.</hi> to fix his Aſſertion upon, Note</p>
               <p n="1">1. THAT in <hi>our Author</hi>'s ſenſe the diſpleaſure of God againſt the very perſon of a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever, and that for ſin even in a penal ſenſe, abides with God whilſt the ſaid Believer is in this mortal ſtate, not the beſt of Believers being without the ſame, during their abode in the fleſh; whence it ſhrewdly follows, That when they are compleatly ſanctified and freed from all the indwellings of ſin, then and not till then are they got from under God's vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cative and punitive diſpleaſure againſt their <hi>perſons</hi> for the ſame. This with <hi>our Author</hi>'s good leave, I take not only to be his Cryptical reſerve, but downright <hi>Arminianiſm,</hi> as growing in the Soil of a <hi>Self-juſticiary.</hi> Therefore he tells us, <hi>page</hi> 37. How we are to underſtand God's charging of ſin upon a juſtified perſon, <hi>That it ſhall not be his endleſs peril, his utter deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> but it feems it carries and procures that diſpleaſure from God againſt even the perſon of a Believer, that is the ſame in kind with an <hi>endleſs</hi> peril, and <hi>utter</hi> deſtruction; from which diſpleaſure in the everlaſting continuance of the ſame (though not nature thereof du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this Life) the perſon of a Believer may be fully ſecured in a ſtate of perfect Holineſs; But</p>
               <p n="2">2. Moſt abſconded Sir! Methink you ſwell, and that moſt rankly too of the Cask of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinianiſm,</hi> like your Foxes, Fitchets, and ſuch ſort of Vermin, though very recluſely lodged from the Eye, yet their naſty ſcent uſually betrays them; for is it poſſible, That <hi>Chriſt</hi> can be look'd upon as a proper Sacrifice for ſin, and not as undergoing the full diſpleaſure of God againſt, as well as puniſhment from God for the ſame? And if ſo, where would this puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be, or what would it ſignific? This is to make but a meer ſham, Metaphorous appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, or gulling Cheat of the infinite Sufferings of the bleſſed Jeſus, and thereby to deſpoil him of his Glory, even of that Baptiſm that he was in a ſtrait, till he was Baptized with the ſame; nay, let me tell this <hi>Author</hi> by the way, That take away the diſpleaſure of God againſt ſin, or ſuch as are in their Perſons <hi>juridically</hi> charged with the ſame (from which he would acquit <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his <hi>Repreſentative undertaking,</hi> and yet load a Believer withal) and I will rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily undergo the puniſhment thereof.</p>
               <p>By the way, obſerve this as a true <hi>Mark</hi> and <hi>Token</hi> of both an <hi>Arminian</hi> and <hi>Socinian;</hi> that if they can but be ſecured from puniſhment, they do not much value either the Good Will or Diſpleaſure of God. This ſeems to be the ſecret Nurſery of all their irregular Proceedings, both in <hi>frothineſ of Spirit, looſneſs of Life,</hi> and <hi>prevarication in Doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in,</hi> together with their <hi>treacherous management of Authors;</hi> for ſo long as they think that <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath taken away the ſin only in the puniſhment thereof, they little ſet by <hi>(ſelf</hi> being ſecured thro' the ſame) what becomes either of the Favour or Diſplicency of God towards them, unleſs they can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the former in their own way, unto which Chriſt ſhall give them a remote aſſiſtance, they are very regardleſs, until the appearance of a Death's-head drive them to their <hi>Tutiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum eſt,</hi> &amp;c.—<hi>Verbum ſat ſapienti.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take this that follows in a familiar compariſon, as a ſhort, yet full <hi>Scheme</hi> of the <hi>Neono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mian Hereſie,</hi> touching the <hi>Doctrin of Juſtification,</hi> yea, the whole Body of that <hi>Divinity</hi> included in the <hi>definition</hi> given therein of the <hi>Covenant of Grace:</hi> That as a <hi>Surety</hi> on the <hi>behalf of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> Compounds for his <hi>Debt,</hi> by <hi>cancelling the Bond,</hi> as to its immediate Relation between the <hi>Creditor and Debtor,</hi> in <hi>tranſlating</hi> over the Charge unto <hi>himſelf</hi> by <hi>his undertaking</hi> for the payment thereof, after the way of a <hi>Briſtol-Bargain,</hi> unto which the ſaid <hi>Surety</hi> enables him by a proviſion of all Implemental materials, together with his derective advice, continued Preſence, and recruitive Aſſiſtances upon failures, till the poor <hi>Debtor,</hi> by vertue of the ſame at the end of his <hi>Seventh</hi> Year of <hi>Jubilee,</hi> receives his compleat diſcharge, which he (as ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely diſowning all abilities in himſelf to compaſs the ſame) fully aſcribes, and that juſtly as well as thankfully, in the whole of it, unto the meritorious reſponſibleneſs of undiſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed kindneſs, and conſtant actual ſupplies from his merciful Spouſer and Undertaker. Thus in their ſenſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> becomes our <hi>Surety.</hi> Now our <hi>Author, Ibid.</hi> comes to his Journey-man-Taylor's unſtitching conceſſions, tho' not half ſo honeſtly, yet as boobiſhly as poſſibly can be,—<q>Here we moſt readily grant, that thoſe who are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied <note place="margin">Criſpi. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmask'd, Pag.</hi> 37.</note> clear from the Imputation of all ſin, according to ſome Scriptures he quotes, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 7. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 24. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 1, 33. But hereupon ariſes
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51623:17"/> two <hi>Queſtions,</hi> notwithſtanding this his <hi>Armini-S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cinian</hi> Grant, as to the ends and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances attending the ſame.</q> As,</p>
               <p>Queſt. 1. <hi>Whether or no any one yet was, or ever ſhall b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> truly juſtified without a praevious juri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical Title unto, and intereſt in ſuch a Righteouſneſs (and that without a preſent Work of Grace within him) as may conſtitute him compleatly juſt as to the matter thereof, and alſo render and make it appear, that God is infinitely juſt in the Juſtification of ſuch a one?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Queſt. 2. <hi>Whether this Conceſſion of our</hi> Author, <hi>as to the</hi> Imputation of all Sin unto Chriſt, <hi>and yet reſerving even that thereof, which is</hi> Hell <hi>it ſelf, unto a true Believer; That in his Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, and Afflictions, he undergoes the very</hi> Diſpleaſure of God, <hi>and</hi> Chriſt only the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>be in the leaſt conſiſtent with Truth, common Senſe, or ſolid Peace and Comfort? Our</hi> Author <hi>laying a greater Burthen upon the Believer in this his</hi> Conceſſion, <hi>than upon Chriſt himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="charge">
               <head>But further he tells us in the <hi>Eighth Charge.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VIII. <hi>That this reminds him of another aſſertion of the Doctor</hi>'s, viz. p. 38. <hi>as a natural con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent of his former poſition.</hi> And ſo it is as natural indeed as our <hi>Author</hi>'s Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings againſt him, the former defending Truth with Truth, the latter ſeeking to undermine the ſame by a continued Multiplication of one treachery on the back of the other. Before we come to a preciſe conſideration of his quotations, note theſe three things:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That when he cites the <hi>Doctor</hi> for ſaying, <hi>That no Believer is puniſhed or afflicted for ſin,</hi> he hides from thee his not only inferential, but alſo literal explanation of the ſame, <hi>p.</hi> 38, 39.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That when he is forced to ſpeak, even the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s words, (as not being able to avoid the ſame (no more than <hi>Bal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am</hi> could avoid his <hi>Propheſie)</hi> wherein his conſciouſneſs appears like the Devils of old, in their owning of <hi>Chriſt,)</hi> which are fully expreſſive of his meaning againſt what our <hi>Author</hi> diſcerpts out of him as the matter of his accuſation againſt him; he would caſt the imputation of Weakneſs and Fallacy upon him, meerly to make way for the recepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his invidious and ungrounded ſtroke againſt him, and thereupon gives us ſuch a diſquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive explication of the matter in hand, as roundly beſpeaks <hi>himſelf</hi> to be both a <hi>Fool</hi> &amp; <hi>Cheat. p.</hi> 40.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That in his Conceſſions, even from his quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation of Scriptures themſelv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, he unravels the whole, and thereby ſubſcribes unto the <hi>Doctor,</hi> yea, confirms him againſt all his falſe Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachments. This Charge being much of the ſame nature with the former (which our <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> himſelf conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es) I ſhall contr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct my ſelf as briefly as I can in <hi>my remarks</hi> upon the ſame.</p>
               <p>THE firſt the <hi>Doctor</hi> himſelf confirms, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d that in the very place, from whence our <hi>Author</hi> quotes him. <hi>p.</hi> 17, 8. 170. 258, In all which plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s the <hi>Doctor</hi> aſſerts two things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That all the Afflictions and Troubles that b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fall a B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liever, cannot expi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te or ſatisfie for the leaſt Sin.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That God in his puniſhing of a Believer doth it not in a proper vindicative ſenſe, as juridicall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> charged with Sin, to drive him from Sin: All which our <hi>Author</hi> doth as much MASK from thy Sight as poſſibly he can, as knowing, that had he done otherwiſe, he muſt with his own Pen, have overthrown, and daſht out the whole of this his invidious enterprize; for proof of which, take the following <hi>Quotations.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>Chriſt is a way to take away the <hi>effect</hi> of God's diſpleaſure; Chriſt is the only way to take it away. <hi>Shall I give the Fruit of my Body?</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Micah</hi> 6. 7. <hi>for the ſin of my Soul; a Thouſand Rams, or Ten Thouſand Rivers of</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi>'s <hi>Works,</hi> Vol. I. Serm. 2. Pag. 17, 18.</note> 
                     <hi>Oyl?</hi> No, alaſs, this will not buy out the penance of one Sin, when he hath ſinned; it is all too mean a price; there muſt be a better to take away that Wrath; that is, the heavy puniſhment of God fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever. I ſay, a better price than this, not a dearer price to us poor Men, but yet a more dear and acceptable price unto God, a price in its nature Infinite and Invaluable, but of this price, not a Farthing goes out of our purſe; there is the greatneſs. <hi>Chriſt is a way to</hi> take away all Wrath, in reſpect of the heavy hand of God, which is the Fruit of Man's ſin.</p>
                  <p>IN brief, Beloved, the ſum plainly is this, <hi>Chriſt is ſo the Way from Wrath</hi> (Now our <hi>Author</hi>'s Charge comes in, as it lies in this Parentheſis. <hi>That God doth never puniſh any Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever after he is a Believer; for ſin,)</hi> I ſay, God doth not puniſh him <hi>for ſin.</hi> This ſeems to be a hard Propoſition to many; but give me leave to clear what I ſay, and ſo according to the clear evidence of truth, reject or receive what I deliver to you. In <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. 5. a Chapter of moſt admirable <hi>Excellency,</hi> to ſet forth the wonderful incomprehenſible benefit of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51623:18"/> 
                     <hi>Chriſt:</hi> Obſerve it, <hi>He was wounded for our Tranſgreſſions,</hi> mark the puniſhment, <hi>He was bruiſed for our Iniquities; the Chaſtiſement of our Peace was upon him; and by his ſtripes we are healed.</hi> Now beloved, I will ask but this <hi>Queſtion;</hi> Are the Wounds of Chriſt, part only of our puniſhment? Or are they the whole of our puniſhment? The Bruiſings of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> were they to be part of the puniſhment our ſins deſerved? If they were but part we muſt bear the reſt our ſelves; but then we muſt be Co-Saviours with Chriſt, Co-bearers of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation and Wrath, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63. 3. <hi>He hath troden the Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e-preſs alone,</hi> ſaith the Text; <hi>he looked for ſome that might help, and wondred, and there was none, v.</hi> 5. No Creature in the World was able to be a helper with him</p>
                  <p>I ſpeak of Believers only, they do not bear one laſh of that deſerved Wrath that is poured out for ſin, not one laſh nor ſtroke; Chriſt trod it alone himſelf. Yea, but you will ſay unto me, <hi>Doth not God afflict his Children and Believers? All the World ſeeth and knoweth he doth; therefore why ſpeak you againſt this?</hi> Beloved, give me leave to ask you, Is there not a great deal of difference between God's afflicting of Believers, and God's pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing of Believers for ſin? <hi>(Here our Author comes in)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Queſt.<hi>Are not the afflictions of Believers for their ſins?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I <hi>Anſwer.</hi> No; Afflictions are unto Believers from ſin, but not for ſin: What is the meaning of that will you ſay? This, God in afflicting of Believers, doth not intend to puniſh them, as now laying on them the deſert of their ſin; for that is laid upon Chriſt; but he doth afflict them in part to be a help to preſerve them from ſin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It may be in affliction, and when the Rod of God is fallen upon thee, thy heart will be ready to raiſe ſuch thoughts as theſe in thee: <hi>Now God</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Criſp<hi>'s Works, Vol.</hi> I <hi>Ser.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 170.</note> 
                     <hi>will be even with me: now ſhall I ſmart for my tranſgreſſions.</hi> (Thus far <hi>our Author.)</hi> But know this, that at that inſtant, when God brings Afflictions upon thee, he doth not remember any ſin of thine; they are not in his thoughts towards thee; for the Text ſaith, not only of the preſent inſtant, that God doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them; but of the future alſo, nay, of the everlaſting future: <hi>Your ſins, and your iniquities, I will remember no more.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I beſeech you, conſider this one thing, you that think that God doth plague and puniſh you, being Believers, for ſuch and ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſins of yours, and ſay, Doth not God now remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber theſe ſins of mine? Doth God puniſh ſuch and ſuch ſins in others, and take venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance for them, and doth he not remember them? Doth God uſe to do things hand over head? Doth God lay his Rod and his Scourge upon them, and never think of the cauſe of it? And if theſe Afflictions be the Judgment of God for theſe ſins, certainly God muſt remember theſe ſins, and ſo know them as Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ives and Provocations, to inflict ſuch Vengeance upon them, and if God doth puniſh them for them, certainly God doth now remember them: And what of all this? Is it a Truth that God hath ſpoken, <hi>Your iniquities, and your ſins will I remember no more?</hi> Then ſurely, whatſoever things befall the <hi>Children of God,</hi> are not puniſhments for ſin, they are not remembrances of ſin, the Lord muſt be true and faithful in his Covenant; and therefore, if Men ſhall cavil againſt this Free-Grace of God, yet let me requeſt this of you, Let the evidence of the Holy Ghoſt ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with your Spirits, that if any Creature in Heaven or Earth, Men or Angels, ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to contradict this, let them be accounted as they deſerve. Let all give way to this Truth; if any thing in the World can make it appear to the contrary, then let it go away with it: But if the Spirit of God doth ſpeak it ſo clearly, that nothing can be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected againſt it; let not any thing cauſe thee to live in ſo much darkneſs and uncomfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs, as thou muſt do, till thou receive this Grace of the Lord.</p>
               </q>
               <p>Now, <hi>Reader,</hi> Be thine own Judge, and thou wilt find that this <hi>Author,</hi> even in this his particular dealing with <hi>the Dr.</hi> would overthrow two main Pillars of our <hi>Religion,</hi> as</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The <hi>compleat ſatisfaction of Chriſt,</hi> as it reſpects <hi>ſin</hi> in the full demerits of the ſame.</item>
                  <item>2. The <hi>Grace of God</hi> himſelf in the free and full ſovereign application thereof unto <hi>Elect</hi> Sinners.</item>
               </list>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>See Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> on <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 6. <hi>Vol.</hi> IV.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. That love is antecedent unto chaſtening; <hi>he chaſtens whom he loves;</hi> ſo it is with any Father, he hath firſt the love of a Father before he chaſten his Son; <q>whatever therefore
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51623:18"/> is the ſame materially with the chaſtiſement of children, if it be where the <hi>Love of Adoption,</hi> doth not precede, is puniſhment <hi>(mark here Reader)</hi> The love therefore here in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ended, is the love of Adoption, that is, the love of Benevolence, whereby he makes men his children, and his love of complacency in them when they are ſo.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtiſing is an effect of his love. It is not only conſequential unto it, but ſprings from it, <q>wherefore there is nothing properly poenal in the chaſtiſements of Believers: pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment proceeds from love unto Juſtice, not from love unto the perſon puniſhed. Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement is from love to the perſon chaſtiſed, though mixed with diſpleaſure againſt his ſin.</q> Note here, <hi>Reader,</hi> with an eſpecial Note, That the perſon of a Believer is not diſpleaſed with, though under the chaſtiſement, not puniſhment, of the Lord for ſin. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſaid <hi>Dr</hi> further tells us, on <hi>v.</hi> 9, 10. <q>That the eſpecial end of God in Divine Chaſtiſements is, that he may make us partakers of his holineſs.</q> And on <hi>v.</hi> the <hi>11th.</hi> he fur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her ſheweth the benefit of chaſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ements; And is not all this Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi>'s own Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> in a poe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al ſenſe, but from ſin, that God afflicts his People, or that he is diſpleaſed with their perſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, whilſt he doth afflict them.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond thing no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed in this Charge, is in <hi>Page</hi> 40. where <hi>our Author</hi> gives us <hi>the Dr</hi>'s reaſon why God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oth not afflict or puniſh any Believer for fin; namely, <q>becauſe <hi>Chriſt bor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ll the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>niſhment due to ſin; and if he bore all, we can bear none: God w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ld not puniſh Chriſt and B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lievers too.</hi>
                     </q> (And he endeavours to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>validate <note place="margin">Criſp. <hi>unmask'd. page</hi> 40.</note> it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> as notable a <hi>Socinian diſtinction,</hi> ſaving the blockiſhneſs of it, as moſt I have m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t with. <q>Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſeems (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s he) to be a plauſible reaſon, but it hath no ſolid Foundation. It is in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ed a meer F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>llacy, which I prove thus; To argue after this manner, <hi>Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> bore all Puniſhment due to Sin, therefore Believers have none to bear,</hi> is ſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ecedent Propoſition ſpeaks not of the <hi>ſame bearing of puniſhment</hi> that the co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſequent Prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſition ſpeaks of. The one ſpeaks of bearing puniſhment, as that pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment was a full ſatisfaction to God for ſin, but the other ſpeaks of bearing puniſhment as 'tis the deſert of ſin.</q> Now thinking he hath come off with Flying Colours, he tells us, <hi>Here is a vaſt difference between theſe two.</hi> And indeed there is, but not in <hi>our Author</hi>'s ſenſe, as I humbly conceive. <q>It ſeems therefore, (ſays he) that there is a bearing of puniſhment, as a full ſatisfaction to God for ſin, this Chriſt bore; but there is alſo (ſays he) another bearing of puniſhment, and that as it is the deſert of ſin; this the ſinner bears.</q> He further tells us, that it is no good conſequence to ſay, <hi>That if Chriſt bore all the ſufferings due to ſin, then we muſt bear none.</hi> This might paſs for a pretty Quibble, were there not ſo much as thou wilt find of helliſh Blaſphemy lodged in it; for what of puniſhment for ſin did Chriſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo, if the full, compleat deſert thereof was not laid upon him? And if this was not inflicted upon him to the very uttermoſt, that an infinitely Divine Hand of offended Juſtice could exact, how was God or Juſtice ſatisfied? But <hi>Sir,</hi> we ken your meaning very well, That Sin was not the meritorious, but impulſive cauſe of the Death of Chriſt; which in plain terms, is to aſſign no more unto his Death, but what is incident unto Nature, upon Its diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution; and therefore be pleaſed to take home your ſottiſh, as well as wicked diſtinction to your ſelf: It is reckoned upon you as being <hi>reprobate Silver,</hi> and what will by no means paſs amongſt <hi>the Shekels of the Sanctuary.</hi> And notwithſtanding his ſubſequent paring of this his Aſſertion, ſo as to take off its more apparent rough-hewedneſs, which in the ſubſtance thereof doth more than once drop from him; it is for no other end than that it may with the more undiſcernedneſs paſs off like poiſon in a Glaſs of Wine.</p>
                  <p>The third thing in this Charge is, The Scriptures he produces againſt the <hi>Doctor,</hi> which evidently make for him, as <q>
                        <hi>Lev.</hi> 26. 18, 24, 28. <hi>Ez.</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Criſp. <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmask'd, p,</hi> 41, 42, 43, 44.</note> 9. 13. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. 39. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>os</hi> 3. 2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 30, 31, 32. <hi>Iſa</hi> 27. 9.</q> Not one of theſe Texts beſpeaks <hi>God's diſpleaſure</hi> againſt the <hi>Perſons of Believers,</hi> or his bringing Afflictions upon <hi>them</hi> in a <hi>penally-vindicative</hi> ſenſe, ſome expreſſing warnings, ſome duties actually cloſed with, as ſtirred up thereunto by them, ſome duties to be engaged in and under them, ſome gracious effects from and thorow them. And that of the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> is but the ſame with that of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah,</hi> and King <hi>Joſiah:</hi> now will any one ſay, that this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from God's looking upon thoſe of them that were true Believers, as not having their Sins in the full deſert as well as puniſhment of them upon Chriſt; for which it is that the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:51623:19"/> 
                     <hi>Doctor</hi> expreſſes himſelf in thoſe curtail'd Quotations that our <hi>Author</hi> brings againſt him. See Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> on <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. 11. And now our <hi>Author,</hi> after all his pitiful ſttuff, tells us, <hi>p.</hi> 45. <q>That he will not here nicely diſpute about the Nature of puniſhment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="charge">
               <head>AS to the <hi>Ninth Charge.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IX. He tells us, that—<q>It is not only aſſerted by him, <hi>(i. e.</hi> the <note place="margin">Criſp. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmask'd, Pag.</hi> 47.</note> 
                     <hi>Doctor)</hi> that <hi>God is not offended or diſpleaſed with Believers,</hi> much leſs <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth</hi> them for their Sins; but he holds likewiſe, that <hi>God is not pleaſed with any of their Graces and Duties,</hi> or whatever good thing they do, although theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the Holy Spirit, the Author of all Goodneſs.</q> Now, ſhould our <hi>Author</hi> have but his mind, by a juſt rule of conſequence, the Spirit of God muſt take place of the <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator,</hi> and the Graces and Duties of Believers ſtand in the very room, and ſtead of the <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Chriſt.</hi> This will appear evidently from the places whence he fetches the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his Poyſon againſt the <hi>Doctor,</hi> or rather the Truths that the <hi>Doctor</hi> aſſerts. As,—<q>A Man would think that the Apoſtle contradicted himſelf; works have nothing to do in Man's Salvation, or move God to ſave;</q> 
                  <hi>Not of Works,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Criſp's <hi>Works, Vol.</hi> II. <hi>Ser.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 321.</note> ſaith he, <hi>but of Grace;</hi> yet ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>You are created and ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to good Works;</hi> theſe ſtand well together. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> tells <q>
                     <hi>Titus,</hi> that Men ſhould <hi>ſtudy good Works, for theſe are profitable unto Men:</hi> A Man ſerves his Generation, while he walketh in good Works, and he doth good too to them, among whom he lives. A Man ſerves not himſelf in all the good Works he doth; for the Lord Chriſt hath fully ſerved his turn already; either we muſt make our Performance Chriſt's, or elſe we muſt diſclaim them. What a Pride and Arrogance is this, either Men will rule the Roaſt, or elſe they will not abide in the Houſe! As every Man hath his Office in a Family, ſo every thing in Man hath its Office: Good Works have very neceſſary Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices in the Family, but they were never ordained to be <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s, much leſs to be <hi>God</hi>'s. When Chriſt was tempted by the <hi>Phariſees</hi> about Tribute, he makes this reply; <hi>Give unto</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Caeſar's, <hi>and unto God the things that are God</hi>'s. Let not the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>en encroach upon God, to take God's Work upon its ſelf; I tell you, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, we know not the evil of theſe vain Imaginations. Should the Lord deal with you according to your own Hearts, that as your Performances could lay ſins upon Chriſt, and diſcharge you, ſo you ſhould be diſcharged, when would you ever lay them upon him, when (alaſs) inſtead of laying old Sins upon Chriſt, by new performance, you do but add new ſins to old; all our Righteouſneſs is but renovation of new tranſgreſſion to the old. <hi>For all ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Righteouſneſs,</hi> ſaith the Lord by the Prophet <hi>Eſay, even all our Righteouſneſſes,</hi> he he ſpeaks of every particular, <hi>they are as filthy Rags, and a menſtruous Cloth.</hi> Is this the way to eaſe a Man of his Sin, to throw dirt anew in the Face of God? Is this a way for a Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to get the King's Pardon, to come into the Kings Preſence, and throw Poiſon in the King's Face? There is not one Righteous Action a Man doth perform, but he doth therein anew throw Dirt in the Face of God by that Action of his, becauſe <hi>Sin,</hi> (as the Wiſe-man ſaith) <hi>is abomination to the Lord.</hi> Who knows the Errors of his Life, and the Multitude of his failings in the beſt Righteouſneſs he doth? Man's Righteouſneſs may ſerve the turn of Men, but it will never ſerve God's Turn. Tho' there be failing in our Righteouſneſs, yet it may be profitable to Men, but as there are failings in it, the Eyes of God cannot away with it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Now let me add this unto what the <hi>Dr.</hi> ſays, That were our inward righteouſneſs unſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly perfect, even in this life, yet I will be bound to clear and maintain, and that from the full diſtinct tenure and ſcope of the <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> That for the ſame, neither would our perſons be accepted with, as juſtified before God, no nor any of our duties, either in whole or in part be regarded by him; for take but that righteouſneſs away for which this worthy <hi>Dr.</hi> ſo well pleads, both as to its matter and uſe, and this <hi>our Author</hi> together, with the reſt of <hi>his diſſembling Tribe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> would wholly ſubvert (unleſs it be from a <hi>meritorious</hi> ſtation which they are pleaſed to aſſign unto it for fear of the worſt) and there is not the <hi>moſt glorified Saint in Heaven,</hi> but would ſoon turn <hi>Apoſtate;</hi> for this is their clothing; it is herein, as well as hereon their eternal <hi>Station</hi> lies: This is the Robe in which God beholds them, they become <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>pted with him, and he well-pleaſed with them, without which, even their holineſs (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:51623:19"/> they are qualified to take in the Glory of God, and alſo to rejoice in him) would ſoon be blaſted, dwindled away, and come to nothing, nay, eternal wrath would ſeize upon them. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 9. <hi>Malachi</hi> 4. 2. <hi>Zach.</hi> 3. 2, 3, 4. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 7, 21. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 18. <hi>ch.</hi> 4. 4. <hi>ch.</hi> 7. 9, 13. <hi>chap.</hi> 15. 6. <hi>ch.</hi> 19. 8, 14. This was the conſtant joy of him, that was counted a Man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God's own Heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71. 16: Herein his Spirit was perpetually exerciſed. Nay, it is the very property or diſtinguiſhing character of the new Creature, eſpecially the leading Member thereof, to eye this, to bring this night, to ſee that the Soul be clothed clad with, and wrapt in the ſame, unto this the Winding-ſtairs of the <hi>Temple,</hi> even the Promiſes, as they are in Chriſt, do lead us, and the more we aſcend by Faith, the more ſhall we ſee the Glory of God, experimentally know intereſt in him, and be diſpirited of proud ſelf, <hi>That God in Chriſt may be All in All,</hi> Rom. 1. 17. 1 Cor. 1. 29, 30, 31.</p>
               <p>Again, our <hi>Author</hi> quotes the <hi>Doctor.</hi>—</p>
               <q>
                  <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> complains, That e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en he when he would do Good, Evil was preſent with him, thro' the Law in his Members, rebelling againſt the Law of his Mind, which makes <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Criſp<hi>'s Works, Vol.</hi> II. <hi>Serm.</hi> 1. <hi>Pag.</hi> 232, 234.</note> him cry out of himſelf bitterly againſt all he did: <hi>O wretchrd Man that I am, who ſhall deliver me from this body of Death? (Rom.</hi> 7. 21, 23, 24.) By this Body of Death, he muſt needs mean altogether, becauſe he doth not fly to good Works as a refuge againſt the evil, but to Chriſt alone, as a Refuge againſt all. <hi>I thank God</hi> (ſaith he then) <hi>through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> ver, 25. ſo then in reſpect of the inſeparable Communicative, poyſonfulneſs of the Ingredients of our Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, mingling themſelves with the beſt Righteouſneſs of the beſt Men, both they and their Righteouſneſs are but loſs and dung, and are filthy Rags, and muſt be ſo counted.</p>
                  <p>Some then may object, <hi>If it be ſo, we ought to refrain from doing Righteouſneſs, we muſt refrain from Dung.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwer, that it follows not; but therefore we muſt refrain from glorying in, or ſtroaking our ſelves for our Righteous Doings, and rather take ſhame to our ſelves when we have done, and ſo glory in the Lord. Though good works done by us are but dung in themſelves, and in God's Eye, yet muſt we be careful to maintain good Works, for they are profitable to Men, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 8. though but Loſs and Dung. <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 16. 2, 3. confeſſeth that his Goodneſs extendeth not to God, yet for all this he refrains no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, becauſe it could extend to the Saints that are upon Earth, and to the excellent in whom was his delight. It is no good Plea; That becauſe a Man cannot be wholly clean, therefore he will be more filthy than needs. You will not like it, that becauſe your Children cannot come from School without ſome dirt, in the eleaneſt way; that therefore they ſhall wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low like Swine over Head and Ears in Dirt.</p>
                  <p>Others will ſay, <hi>God often ſhews his Approbation of good Works, which he could not do, if they were all Dung.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwer, that whatſoever is not of Faith is Sin; but as to the Believer, all things are clean. <hi>(Here comes our Author)</hi> So through our Faith in Chriſt, the whole Filth and Dung, of our Works is extracted by Chriſt; and he preſenting the ſame, purged by himſelf alone they became accepted with God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 4.—But ſimply the works themſelves, as done, tho' never ſo well, are abhorred of God, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> never takes them to purge till we our ſelves wholly renounce them by counting them Loſs and Dung; and that acceptance procured by Chriſt, imports only a liking God takes to them, no Efficacy at all they have with him.</p>
                  <p>Again, But you will ſay again, <hi>Chriſt makes our Righteouſneſs to be</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Criſp<hi>'s Works, Vol.</hi> II. <hi>Serm.</hi> 6. <hi>Pag.</hi> 322, 323.</note> 
                     <hi>accep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> makes it pleaſing and acceptable, by purging away all the Filth that is in it, and then it may pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>vail with God to lay our Iniquities upon Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwer <hi>(Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> our Author comes in with his Charge)</hi> It is true, Chriſt doth purge away all the filthineſs, both of Righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eouſneſs and Unrighteouſneſs in Believers; but he doth not purge away the filthineſs of their Righteouſneſs, (that this Righteouſneſs may prevail with God to lay Iniquity upon Chriſt) but then, that Righteouſneſs may be accepted in the Beloved, as Services, Himſelf was without ſpot of the leaſt Sin, yet he takes not away the Iniquity, by laying it upon the himſelf; and if our Righteouſneſs be made compleat, by his taking away the Filth of it, and putting his own perfection on it,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:51623:20"/> it is not to that end that Iniquities may be laid upon Chriſt by it, but that it may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted in way of ſervice.</p>
                  <p>I ſhould go yet one ſtep higher, and let you know, that as it is the Lord alone that lay iniquity upon Chriſt, ſo not only all our performances are unable to lay iniquity upon Chriſt; but even our <hi>Faith and Believing</hi> it ſelf doth not lay iniquity upon Chriſt: Ye may eaſily perceive, Beloved, what I drive at in all this Diſcourſe, namely; to ſtrip the Creature ſtark naked, to leave it ſhiftleſs, and unable any way to help it ſelf, that all the help that the Creature doth receive, may appear to be of the Free-Grace of God meerly, without the Creature's concurrence in it. I ſay therefore, it is not the <hi>Faith</hi> of Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers that doth lay their iniquities upon Chriſt. Suppoſe thou haſt committed many ſins, and thy ſins are apparent and plain; thou wouldſt be rid of theſe tranſgreſſions, and hear of them no more; what is the way? <hi>Works are not of power to do it,</hi> you will ſay, <hi>But Faith is able to diſcharge the ſoul, and quit it from all tranſgreſſions, and lay them upon Chriſt.</hi> But I muſt tell you, albeit God hath given many glorious fruits and effects to Faith, and made it inſtrumental of much excellent and abundant conſolation to his People, yet hath he not honoured Faith with this, that it ſhould lay iniquity on Chriſt, or move God to do it.</p>
                  <p>Now thou mayſt ſee, <hi>Reader,</hi> wherein the fallacy of our <hi>Doeg,</hi> or <hi>malicious Author does ly;</hi> for that which he lays as the foundation of this his <hi>Ninth Charge</hi> againſt <hi>the Dr.</hi> he quotes from <hi>p.</hi> 322. where the <hi>Dr.</hi> ſpeaking of the beſt of Man's Righteouſneſs, that it will not ſerve God's turn, as the matter of our Juſtification before him, he preſently diverts the ſame from the <hi>Dr</hi>'s li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eral, expreſs ſenſe and meaning therein, <hi>That God is not therefore pleaſed with any of the Graces or Duties of his People:</hi> A moſt ungrounded, impudent falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood! But this is the manner of the Man throughout the whole of his Treatiſe, and now that the <hi>Dr.</hi> declares, which way they become of uſe unto us, and acceptable with God; namely, by Chriſt's purging and extracting out of them the filth that does attend them, and ſo preſenting them to the Father, and that, when this is done, yet none of this is that for which God is prevailed with to lay ſin upon Chriſt; He tells us, that <hi>Truth had at laſt got ſuch a forcible prevalency upon the</hi> Dr. <hi>That he recants what he before had ſaid, and withal, that the latter is a vain ſurmiſe in the</hi> Dr. <hi>againſt ſome that would be accounted the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt</hi> Proteſtants, <hi>viz. That Chriſt doth not purge away the filthineſs of their Righteouſneſs, that this Righteouſneſs may prevail with God to lay iniquity upon Chriſt.</hi> But their not only pitiful <hi>cauſa ſine qua non,</hi> as <hi>previous</hi> unto <hi>God's imputation of Righteouſneſs</hi> in order unto <hi>Juſtification</hi> fully demonſtrates that there were juſt grounds for this gracious <hi>Dr</hi>'s ſurmiſes, even in his day, as well as now; but alſo that Faith, Repentance, and Sincerity is the very matter of the ſame, though the merit thereof lies in Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>It is no wonder therefore, that <hi>our Author</hi> is ſo much concerned that the <hi>Dr</hi>'s Book is got into ſo many hands, wherein and whereby both his, together with the vile Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as well as Doctrins and Practices of others, are ſo evidently brought to light. And I am fully ſatisfied, that the more they engage in this work, the more they will not only labour in the fire; but vomit out their own ſhame, if there were any amongſt them.</p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="charge">
               <head>Now we come to his <hi>Tenth</hi> and <hi>Laſt Charge,</hi> wherein he telleth us, That</head>
               <p>X. <q>And Laſtly, another wild Poſition which theſe <hi>Sermons</hi> maintain is this, That <hi>All is done from Eternity, and ſo nothing is to be done now.</hi> He often tells his Auditors, <hi>Your Buſineſs is done to your hand already:</hi> Therefore there is no need of begging for Faith, or any other Grace, or for Forgiveneſs of Sin, or <note place="margin">Criſpi. <hi>unmask'd. p.</hi> 50, 51.</note> any other ſpiritual Priviledge. Theſe are all granted already, and not to be done now. He frequently inculcates this, and in one whole Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon together inſiſts upon it, <hi>viz. That God's pardoning ſinners, and juſtifying the ungodly, are not now, or hereafter to be done; they are not preſent or future, but were diſpatched long ago, even from Eternity.</hi> Whence he infers, that we muſt not look for Remiſſion of Sins, or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification in this Life; we are not to be concerned in any ſuch thing now, we need not be ſolicitous about it, for it is paſt and over: All is done from Eternity.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Now thou mayſt obſerve herein, the Method <hi>our Author</hi> takes in his dealings with <hi>the Dr.</hi> and that in every one of his <hi>Ten Charges</hi> againſt him, not one of them excepted; As</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:51623:20"/> 1. When he lays down any one of them all againſt the <hi>Dr.</hi> he fixes upon ſome diſcerpt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, dragg'd Sentence or Poſition of his, and thereon lays his load of <hi>Invectives,</hi> by moſt falſe and <hi>violent inferences,</hi> endeavouring to ſuit it (by forcing it to ſpeak what it never was deſigned for) to the nature of that Charge he is more immediately upon. But then</p>
               <p n="2">2. Finding by the <hi>Dr</hi>'s Explanation of the ſaid Poſition or Sentence, That his, <hi>viz. our Author</hi>'s Treachery would more openly appear, he reſerves the ſaid explanation or expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the ſame unto the latter end of every one of his Chages, that thereby he might the more undiſcernedly repreſent him as an <hi>Impoſtor, Recanter,</hi> and one <hi>inconſiſtent with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf:</hi> Having put before a quite contrary conſtruction upon it (meerly to blind the eyes of his <hi>Reader)</hi> to what the <hi>Dr.</hi> produces it for. Thus having clapt his own ſenſe to what he has partially pickt out of the <hi>Dr</hi>'s work, he runs and ſetches what the <hi>Dr.</hi> urges to clear and prove the ſame both by Scripture and Argument to render him the vileſt cheat, and moſt vainglorious Perſon imaginable. This I will be bound to make good even to <hi>our Author</hi>'s Face, if he dares openly appear in this Cauſe. As for inſtance, he quotes the <hi>Dr. ut ſuprà, Vol.</hi> II. <hi>Serm.</hi> 8. <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>God's pardoning ſinners, and juſtifying the ungodly are not now or hereafter to be done, &amp;c.</hi> And thereupon <hi>our Author</hi> fixed his virulent ſenſe, <hi>ut priùs</hi> 
                  <q>that we muſt not look for Remiſſion of Sins, or Juſtification in this Life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> but retains the Dr's own explanation of them for another <hi>Charge</hi> againſt him, even that of <hi>Fallacy and Recantation,</hi> thus dividing betwixt the <hi>Dr</hi>'s Poſitions and Explications he would make way for the fixing of <hi>Hereſie</hi> upon him on the one hand, and of <hi>Double-dealing</hi> and Deceitfulneſs on the other.</p>
               <p>Therefore I ſhall quote what our <hi>Author</hi> himſelf ſcat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eringly cites out of the <hi>Dr.</hi> for the fore-mentioned ends, and then let the <hi>Reader</hi> determine; as <hi>Auth.</hi>—<q>That God's pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sinners and juſtifying the ungo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly, are not now or hereafter to be done, they are not preſent or future, but were diſpatched long ago, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Quoted in</hi> Criſpiamſ. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmask'd. p.</hi> 51, 52.</note> even from Eternity. God had all this at once in his eye, and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Platform before him, as if all were then in being, he ſets down his own Act of his Royal Aſſent, that for every ſuch Perſon as he had choſen, and for every ſuch Tranſgreſſion that ſhould be committed at ſuch and ſuch a time, by ſuch and ſuch Perſons, he would accept of ſuch a Chriſt, whom he would fit to bear their Tranſgreſſions—As the Elect were in the Eye of the Lord, before they had a real Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence and Being, ſo all their iniquities were laid on Chriſt from Eternity: But it muſt needs be granted, that the particular Application of this Grace to Perſons, that the Lord hath laid mine iniquities, and thine iniquities upon Chriſt individually, muſt needs be in time.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Now what grounds had our <hi>Author</hi> to deal ſo wretchedly falſe with the <hi>Doctor,</hi> as he doth? as to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay, That there is no need of begging for Faith, or any other Grace, or Forgiveneſs of Sin, or any other ſpiritual Priviledge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> this being prefixed to one part of his curtailed bra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch againſt the <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctor,</hi> and to uſher in another part of the ſame, which is the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s Expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the former part, he tells us,—<q>That it fell from the <hi>Doctor's</hi> own Lips and Pen by chance, and that here you ſee he expreſſes it as a <hi>future thing,</hi> that <hi>God would accept of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <q>And then for the third part of his <hi>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tation,</hi> he tells us, That He <hi>(i. e.</hi> the <hi>Doctor)</hi> at length ſubmits to this, which is the real Truth, but which he had boggled at ſo long, and that indeed this is his way very often; he takes a great deal of pains to rear up a Notion, and then of a ſudden pulls it down again.</q> Thus our <hi>Author,</hi> like a cunning <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſter,</hi> to divert his <hi>Reader</hi> from attending upon him in his vileneſs, and manner of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings as conſcious to himſelf of what he had done, (like a Thief on the purſuit of an <hi>Hue and Cry,</hi> leaves his theft with another) would charge them upon the <hi>Doctor.</hi> This is not only the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> Method to <hi>divide and rule,</hi> but alſo the practical dexterity of the <hi>Atheiſt</hi> to undermine the Scripture, endeavouring to make of it a meer ſelf-contradiction: What Peace ſuch Courſes are like to be productive of one day, I think it were well our <hi>Author</hi> did in time conſider. Thus he deals with the <hi>Doctor</hi> in the remainder of his <hi>Charge, p.</hi> 56. 57, 58, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> wherein, by endeavouring to <hi>unmask</hi> others, who fully, plainly, ſoundly and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, as in their proper colours appear in their Writings, he drops down the Vizard of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:51623:21"/> his own Face, verifying the old Maxim, <hi>That there never yet was cheat, but ſooner or latter proved an open expoſed Fool.</hi> Unto the <hi>Reader</hi>'s farther Satisfaction, as to our <hi>Author</hi>'s Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery herein. I ſhall refer him to an impartial diſquiſition, and comparing of both Books together; which by then he has done, he will ſoon be able to determine, on whoſe ſide the Scales turn; for there is not one of thoſe <hi>Authors</hi> he brings againſt the <hi>Doctor,</hi> whoſe Treatiſes I am acquainted with, but fully ſpeak of him, both as to Election, Juſtification, Graces and Duties, which I could with eaſe make to appear, were it my preſent work ſo to do; only this let me add, That amongſt the many ſcores of black characters that he gives the <hi>Doctor,</hi> I know not one of them (as far as I have been informed either) by <hi>Teacher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> or <hi>Authors,</hi> Men, both of ſound Matter and excellent Spirits, to be in a State of Repro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as deriding the new Birth, <hi>(and the like,</hi> &amp;c.) a ſpecial Mark of the Son of the Bond-Woman, <hi>Gen</hi> 21. 9. compare <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 29, 30. And yet, that the <hi>Doctor</hi> in our <hi>Author</hi>'s Judgment, together with his <hi>Prefaces,</hi> ſhould be a good Man, and in Heaven, is to me a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Riddle, unleſs the meaſures they take here be from their owned allowed deceit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ul pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes here, and yet can retain confident hopes of Glory hereafter.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Lye not, but let thy Heart be true to God,</l>
                  <l>Thy M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uth to it, thy Actions to them both,</l>
                  <l>Cowards tell Lies, and thoſe that fear the Rod,</l>
                  <l>The ſtormy working Soul ſpits Lies and Froth.</l>
                  <l>Dare to be true, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thing can need a Lye,</l>
                  <l>A fault, which needs it moſt, grows two thereby.</l>
               </lg>
               <bibl>Herbert<hi>'s</hi> Poems, <hi>pag.</hi> 3.</bibl>
               <lg>
                  <l>Roma, vale, vidi, ſatis eſt vidiſſe; revertar,</l>
                  <l>Cum Caeno, meretrix, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, cinoedus ero.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>GREAT Carbanado'd <hi>Criſp!</hi> What's now thy Crown,</l>
                  <l>And was thy Glory, here is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ampled down.</l>
                  <l>Here is no <hi>Synagouge,</hi> (alaſs!) fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thee,</l>
                  <l>Since Chriſt alone gave Eyes, and made thee ſee.</l>
                  <l>Had'ſt thou but own'd ſome ſub-caeleſtial Cauſe,</l>
                  <l>Heaven mix'd with Earth by ſome Creation-Laws;</l>
                  <l>A Ground-Work, out of Nature for <hi>Free-Grace,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As of her kind, Her Myſteries to place,</l>
                  <l>And in a Logical Phlehotomy</l>
                  <l>Let out thy Notions by Phyloſophy,</l>
                  <l>Thou hadſt been crown'd for thy <hi>Divinity.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But 'tis too late, ſince thou haſt ſcap't the Fire,</l>
                  <l>And yet doſt live unſing'd in thy Attire.</l>
                  <l>Free from <hi>Chaldean</hi> Scent, and rather more</l>
                  <l>Enlarg'd than cramp'd from what thou waſt before.</l>
                  <l>Paſs on <hi>Jehovah</hi>'s Teſt, let <hi>England</hi> know</l>
                  <l>Who are her Worthies, <hi>Shibboleth,</hi> and who</l>
                  <l>Pronounce <hi>Sibboleth.</hi>— Want of this liſp,</l>
                  <l>With ſome impairs thy Credit, <hi>Gracious Criſp!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whilſt others hunger, thirſt, and pant for more</l>
                  <l>Of that, whereof thou haſt an Ocean ſtore.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. Edwards.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb facs="tcp:51623:21"/>
            <head>AN APPENDIX.</head>
            <p>THERE is lately come into my Hands a ſmall Pamphlet, entituled, <hi rend="blackletterType">The Agreement in Doctrin among the Diſſenting Miniſters in</hi> London, <hi rend="blackletterType">Subſcribed Decemb.</hi> 16. 1692. And that as refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring unto the preſent <hi>Debates</hi> againſt the <hi>Diſſenting Miniſters,</hi> juſtly, and very wretchedly occaſioned by one Mr. <hi>Daniel Williams,</hi> in a moſt corrupt piece of his, called, <hi rend="blackletterType">Goſpel Truth Stated and Vindicated, wherein ſome of</hi> Dr. Criſp's <hi rend="blackletterType">Opinions are conſider'd, and the Oppoſite Truths are plainly Stated and Confirmed.</hi> By the ſaid <hi>Author.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the which <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> together with the Circumſtances attending it, I crave my <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Liberty</hi> to fix my <hi>Remarks,</hi> the cauſe in Hand being every Man's concern, whilſt he has ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a regard to the Glory of God, the welfare of his own Soul, or the faithful and undaunted Service that he owes unto his Generation. <hi>Non ſoli mihi natus eram</hi> and ſo leave ſhall every one to determine for himſelf, though in my Judgment, I muſt confeſs (all things conſidered) I never met with a more uſeleſs, un-intelligible, and yet inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aring Engine in all my days. But before we proceed, I ſhall offer thee Dr. <hi>Owen</hi>'s Opinion in things of this nature:—<q>It is an Agreement in words, and the outward found <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Owen <hi>on Hebr.</hi> Vol. II. <hi>Exercit.</hi> p. 127.</note> of them, but the Belief and Profeſſion of the ſame, Truths or Things, that is alone to be valued, all that is beyond ſuch an Agreement, being left at Peace in the Province of <hi>Mutual Forbearance.</hi> An Agreement in words only Parrots may learn; and it will be better amongſt them, than that which is only ſo amongſt Men, becauſe they have no mind to act, diſſenting and contradicting Principles, but as for Men to declare their aſſent unto a certain form of words, and in the mean time in their Minds and Underſtandings, expreſly to judge and condemn the Faith and Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of one another about theſe very things, is a matter that no way tends to the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, Peace, or Edification of the Church: For inſtance, ſuppoſe a form of words, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing in general, that Chriſt was an High<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Prieſt: that the Acts of the Prieſthood being Oblation and Interceſſion, Chriſt in like manner offered himſelf to God, and maketh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for us, that hereby he purgeth, expiateth, and doth away all our ſins, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more expreſſions to the ſame purpoſe, ſhould be drawn up, and ſubſcribed by the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians</hi> and their Adverſaries, as they can ſafely do on all Hands, will this in the leaſt further any Agreement or Unity between us, whilſt we not only diſagree about the ſenſe of all theſe Terms and Expreſſions, but believe that things abſolutely diſtant and inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with one another, yea, deſtructive of one another, are intended in them?</q>
            </p>
            <p>Again <hi>the ſame Author</hi> ſaith,—</p>
            <q>
               <p>Conſidering the <hi>Agreement</hi> in all Fundamental Articles of Faith between theſe Churches, thus at difference, and of what great uſe their Union might be unto the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Owen<hi>'s Enquiry into the Original, Nature, Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Power, Order, and Communion of</hi> Evangelical Churches, <hi>p.</hi> 300.</note> both as unto its Spiritual and Political Intereſt in this World, the effecting of ſuch an Union among them, hath been attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by many. <hi>Private Perſons, Princes, Coll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>quies, or Synods</hi> of ſome of the Parties at variance, have ſedulouſly engaged herein.
<pb facs="tcp:51623:22"/> I wiſh they had never miſſed it in ſtating the Nature of that Union, which in this is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone deſirable, and alone attainable; nor in the Cauſes of that diſadvantageous difference that was between them. For hence it is come to paſs, that although ſome <hi>Verbal Compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> have ſometimes by ſome been conſented unto, yet all things continue practically a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſt them, as they were from the beginning. And there are yet Perſons who are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging Propoſals for ſuch an Union with great Projection in point of <hi>Method</hi> for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing of it, and ſtating of the Principles of Agreement. ſome whereof I have by me. But the preſent State of things in <hi>Europe,</hi> with the Minds of Potentates, not concerned in theſe things, leave little encouragement for ſuch Attempt, for any expectation of any ſucceſs.</p>
               <p>After the Trial and Experience of an <hi>Hundred and Fifty Years,</hi> it is altogether in vain, to be expected that any farther Reconciliation or Union, ſhould be effected between theſe <hi>Proteſtant Churches,</hi> by either Parties, <hi>Relinquiſhment</hi> of the Doctrins they have ſo long taught, profeſſed, and contended for, or of their <hi>Practiſe</hi> in Divine Worſhip, which they have ſo long been accuſtomed unto. We may as well expect a River ſhould run, back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, as expect any ſuch things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 302, That all theſe <hi>differing Churches,</hi> and whilſt theſe Differences do continue, be taught to prefer their <hi>general I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tereſt,</hi> in oppoſition unto the Kingdom of <hi>Satan,</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt</hi> in the World, before the leſſer things wherin they differ, and thoſe occaſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l Animoſities that will enſue upon them. It hath been obſerved in many places, that the nearer ſome Men or Churches come together in their <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 302, 303.</note> Profeſſion, the more diſtant they are in their Affections; as the <hi>Lutheraus</hi> in many places do more hate the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> than the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> I hope it is not ſo by us. This makes it evident, that the want of neceſſary <hi>Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> amongſt Churches, doth not proceed from the things themſelves wherein they differ, but from the Corrupt Luſts and I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of the Perſons that differ. This Evil can no otherwiſe be cured but by ſuch a <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> as ſhall in ſome meaſure reduce <hi>Primitive</hi> Simplicity, Integrity and Love, ſuch as were among the Churches of the converted <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> when they walked accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto the ſame <hi>Rule,</hi> in what they had attained, forbearing one another in Love, as unto the things wherein they differed. Until this alſo be effected, all endeavours for further Union, whilſt theſe differences continue (as they are like to do, unleſs the whole frame of things in <hi>Europe</hi> ſhould be changed by ſome great Revolution) will be fruitleſs and uſeleſs.</p>
               <p>Were this conſcientiouſly inſiſted on, out of a pure Love unto Jeſus Chriſt, with Zeal, for his Glory, it would not only be of more uſe than innumerable <hi>wrangling Diſputes</hi> about the points in difference, but more than the <hi>exacteſt Methods,</hi> in contriving <hi>Formularies,</hi> of Conſent, or <hi>Colloquies,</hi> or <hi>Synodical Conferences</hi> of the Parties at variance, with all their Solemnities, Orders, Limitations, Precautions, Conceſſions and Orations. Let Men ſay what they will, it muſt be the <hi>Revival,</hi> Flouriſhing, and Exerciſe of <hi>Evangelical Light,</hi> Faith and Love, that ſhall heal the Differences and Breaches that are among the Churches of Chriſt; nor ſhall any thing elſe be honoured with any great influence in that work.</p>
            </q>
            <p>From the whole of what our <hi>truly worthy Eleazer,</hi> Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> has, laid before us, I would gather thus much, (who ſo ſtood in the <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. 10. <hi>comp</hi> Dr. Owen<hi>'s Diſcourſe of the Glory of Chriſt,</hi> Part 1. <hi>Pref. latter end.</hi>
               </note> cauſe of his <hi>Lord and Maſter,</hi> till his Hand was weary, and yet quitted it not, but clave unto the Sword, yea, though dead, yet ſtill ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, in the great Victory the Lord wrought by him, even ſuch as that the People have little more to do, ſave to return after him only to the ſpoil.)</p>
            <p>That whatever attempts may be made after an Agreement between <hi>Diſſenting Parties</hi> by a <hi>Subſcrition of Articles,</hi> true in the real form and verbal the matter thereof; yet if the ſcopal deſign, genuin energy, and unſophyſtieated truths contained thereof be not attended unto, and that as ariſing from a divine, clear, irreſiſtible, and yet Heart-bowing and bending Conviction upon the Conſcience, will be ſo far from terminating in their ſatisfaction, as that indeed thereby (all ſuch Hypocritical meaſure being abhorred of God) ſooner or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a wider gap of Difference will be opened, and alſo deeper, and more laſting Exaſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations iſſue from the ſame. Nay, ſuch is the watchful and careful Eye of God over and
<pb facs="tcp:51623:22"/> towards, even his cajoled and deceived ones, that if they will ſtill ſuffer themſelves to be decoyed and gulled by the fair, and yet empty pretences of a certain ſort of profeſſors, he will by one <hi>Providence</hi> or another (as he did by <hi>Lot)</hi> even Fire them out from amongſt ſuch <hi>Aſſociates,</hi> which he has truly begun, and that with the <hi>Fire of his own Sanctuary,</hi> kindled already; for tho' the Embers thereof may ſeem to be covered for the preſent, by the naſty Aſhes of a pretended empty <hi>Agreement</hi> caſt upon them, yet in due time he will break through the ſame by ſuch a flame, as ſhall openly proclaim his <hi>Zeal;</hi> and his being cloathed therewith as a Cloak for his own G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ory, eſtabliſh and confirm his upright ones, and bring a dreadful <hi>Terror</hi> upon the <hi>Hypocrites in</hi> Zion. <hi>I come not to bring Peace, but the Sword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Queſtion to the point in hand will naturally follow, namely—What it is from or in this <hi>Paper of Agreement,</hi> that ſhould provoke any Man's Pen to drop ſo much Diſlatisfaction againſt the ſame and eſpecially conſidering that ſo many and ſo much differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Miniſters</hi> in their Perſuaſions, have been thereby brought into a ſeeming open, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal coaleſcency one with another? Unto which I ſhall give thee my thoughts and attend thy better <hi>Information,</hi> as</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt Ground of my <hi>Diſſatisfaction</hi> herein is, that the <hi>Difference</hi> in hand as to the <hi>Matter</hi> is not at all decided, or attempted to be decided by this <hi>Paper of Agreement, but a difference be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ween Perſons,</hi> wherein it appears that the intereſt of Man is abſolutely (and that by way of juſt conſequence) preferred to the Intereſt of Chriſt, whoſe glory in his abſtracted and unmixed Truths, muſt it ſeems be thereby poſtponed to the carnal welfare, and glaring Peace or Proſperity of Man; as</p>
            <q>
               <p>On <hi>Decem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 19. 1692. This Expedient was brought to a Meeting of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Miniſters,</hi> who unanimouſly expreſſed their Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the following Words, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That theſe Brethren, who at the Deſire of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Miniſters,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Paper of Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Page</hi> 16.</note> ſome Objections againſt Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> his Book, having brought in the above mentioned Expedient for the Accommodation of the Matters in Controverſie. The <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Miniſters</hi> have weighed it, and approve of the ſame. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, it was further <hi>declared by them,</hi> That whereas the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited</hi> Miniſters <hi>Collectively</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and as ſuch, have not been deſired to Approve of Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> his Book: In like manner, they do not by any thing in this Agreement imply an Approbation of Mr <hi>Chauncy</hi> his Writings in this Controverſie: But yet they do rejoice that both Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> and Mr. <hi>Chauncy</hi> have accepted this offered Expedient.</p>
            </q>
            <p>And would not ſuch Meaſures as theſe be reckoned as highly ridiculous, as well as treacherous and falſe, for my Servant inſtead of adjuſting my Concerns, whereon and whereunto I ſend him, as entruſted with the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me, to take up with a bare ſociable <hi>Act</hi> of Fellowſhip and Friendſhip even amongſt thoſe, with and againſt whom my preſent <hi>Debate</hi> and <hi>Controverſie</hi> lies?</p>
            <p>Now is not all this perfect Sophiſtry? Whence ſhould a neceſſity proceed of an <hi>Agreement?</hi> Is it from the Matter in Controverſie, as ſtated in <hi>Polemical</hi> Writings and Argumentations between them, and that about Truths of the firſt Magnitude? Or is it for the deciſion of a perſonal ſcuffle, that this Expedient was formed? For we find no <hi>Agreement in Doctrin</hi> (ſave what is barely ſubſcriptive to the <hi>Articles of others)</hi> mentioned in the leaſt, but that of <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ns,</hi> whilſt all this while their Treatiſes are at War with, and Battling one another, an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> from the allowed <hi>Precautions of both Authors</hi> (as expreſſed in this <hi>Paper of Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gether with their diſtinct Teſtimonies in the ſame; each reſolving to keep his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> But,</p>
            <p n="2">2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cond Ground of my <hi>Diſſatisfaction</hi> herein is, That ſo ſound Articles and Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> Doctrins therein of Faith, ſhould be made a Pretextual Covering of ſuch <hi>Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſin againſt ſuch Truth or Light, and to make a Pander of the latter to ſerve the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the former. Wherefore, leſt any one might ſuppoſe me over-cenſorious in this, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Ground of my <hi>Diſſatisfaction</hi> herein is. That the Matter it ſelf mainly in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> which is not at all touched upon in the <hi>Paper of Agreement,</hi> but perfectly avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> therein ſtill adhering to their own Judgment in what they had written) is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Fundamental, not either Gradual or Circumſtantial, which appears from theſe
<pb facs="tcp:51623:23"/> words,—<q>It is hereby reſpectively declared that neither they, who ſubſcribed that Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation prefixed to Mr: <hi>Williams</hi> his Book, did therein more than ſignifie (as their own words expreſs) <hi>That they judged he had in all that was material, fully and rightly ſtated the Truths and Errors</hi> (this wants proof in a high <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Paper of Agreem. p.</hi> 2.</note> degree) <hi>therein mentioned as ſuch,</hi> without delivering their ſenſe about the <hi>Preface, Explications</hi> or <hi>Proofs</hi> thereunto belonging; which Declaration is not to be eſteemed as a Diſapproval of the ſaid Preface, Explications or Proofs: Nor they, who with Mr. <hi>Chancy,</hi> ſubſcribed the above-ſaid Paper, did therein offer any particular Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (which is a bold falſhood) againſt the ſaid ſtate of Truths and Errors, which yet is not to be underſtood as an Approval of that ſtate of Truth and Errors.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>Reader</hi> conſider, here are <hi>Articles</hi> ſubſcribed unto by Perſons of ſeveral and very diſtinct Judgments, which plainly appears from their ſtedfaſt adherence unto what they had written, notwithſtanding this form of an <hi>Agreement;</hi> for that which they have ſubſcribed unto muſt either be of an indifferent nature, and conſequently a <hi>Medium</hi> of Reconciliation between them, or elſe muſt be obſolutely deciſive of the Controverſie on the one hand or the other, and ſo long as things are thus agitated in the Dark, my beſt <hi>Advice</hi> unto thee is, to compare the <hi>Subſcribed Articles</hi> with the <hi>Treatiſes</hi> writ by each Party, and by the help of the Spirit of the Lord, thou wilt quickly come to know, not only where Truth does ly, but alſo the various interwoven Cheats, by which ſome Perſons would carry on their wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and unconſcionable deſigns this day. <hi>The Lord give thee underſtanding in all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>The <hi>Reader</hi> is deſired to Correct theſe following <hi>Errata</hi>'s, or any other, with his Pen.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>INtroduct:</hi> Page 2. Line 18. <hi>read won't,</hi> for <hi>would.</hi> p. 3. l. 26. <hi>r. caſt down,</hi> for <hi>caſt us.</hi> p. 2. l. 2. <hi>r. its,</hi> for <hi>it.</hi> l. 19. <hi>r. as,</hi> for <hi>ae,</hi> p. 7. l. 15. <hi>r. into the ſtate,</hi> for <hi>in the ſtate. ibid.</hi> l. 39. <hi>r. this Doctor,</hi> for <hi>thy Doctor.</hi> p. 13. l. 38. <hi>r. Sacrifice,</hi> for <hi>Sanctifie.</hi> p. 14. l. 23. <hi>r. Surrep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titious,</hi> for <hi>Surreptatious. ibid.</hi> l. 37. <hi>r. He that hath,</hi> for <hi>He hath.</hi> p. 22. l. 27. <hi>r. make it,</hi> for <hi>for it.</hi> p. 25. l. 6. <hi>r. hence.</hi> l. 45. <hi>r. of God,</hi> for <hi>for God.</hi> p. 27. l. 36. <hi>r. but to drive.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51623:23"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
